<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Sludge Classification Toxicity model (ProtoQSAR-Combase)</Name>
        <Key>SLUDGE_COMBASECLASS</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for toxicity in sludge, specific for biocides</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.0</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_sludge_combaseClass.dat</TS>
        <LocalQMRF>/data/QMRF_sludge_life.pdf</LocalQMRF>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Toxic</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Toxic</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not predicted</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a classification model for toxicity in Activated Sludge, specific for biocides. It has been developed inside the EU LIFE COMBASE project (LIFE15 ENV/ES/416). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/.</Description>
        <Model>A biocide-like chemical space was developed comparing 6512 chemical structures from the Physprop database and 257 chemical structures of biocides from COMBASE database. Five molecular descriptors were selected as filters. These filters were applied to the experimental data found within the different databases from the QSAR Toolbox V 4.2 (https://qsartoolbox.org/).
            Firstly, 94 biocide-like compounds were found by application of the biocide-chemical space, and were used to develop the qualitative model settling the cut-off to discriminate between a toxic and a nontoxic compound in 100 mg/L. The whole dataset was divided into training and validation set randomly and a classification by using Boosted Trees analysis was used for the model development. The descriptors used in the model are the following
            MaxHother: Maximum atom-type H E-State: H on aaCH, dCH2 or dsCH
            MinwHBa: Minimum E-States for weak Hydrogen Bond acceptors
            ETA_BetaP_ns_d: A measure of lone electrons entering into resonance relative to molecular size
            Gats3c: Geary autocorrelation - lag 3 / weighted by charges
            MinsCH3: Minimum atom-type E-State: -CH3
            ATSC4p: Centered Broto-Moreau autocorrelation - lag 4 / weighted by polarizabilities
            SpMax1_Bhm: Largest absolute eigenvalue of Burden modified matrix - n 1 / weighted by relative
            mass
            GATS1i: Geary autocorrelation - lag 1 / weighted by first ionization potential
            The descriptors were calculated, in the original model, by means of the open-source PaDEL libraries.
            Part of their code has been ported in the VEGA libraries to reproduce the descriptors.
        </Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index >= 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>60.0</n_Train>
        <Specificity_Train>0.973</Specificity_Train>
        <Sensitivity_Train>0.783</Sensitivity_Train>
        <Accuracy_Train>0.9</Accuracy_Train>
        <n_Test>34.0</n_Test>
        <Specificity_Test>0.773</Specificity_Test>
        <Sensitivity_Test>0.833</Sensitivity_Test>
        <Accuracy_Test>0.794</Accuracy_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>