<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Fathead Minnow LC50 96h (EPA)</Name>
        <Key>FATHEAD_EPA</Key>
        <Summary>QSAR model for Fathead Minnow LC50 96h (from EPA T.E.S.T software)</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.8</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_fathead_epa.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>-log(mol/l)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction for fathead minnow (Pimephales promelas) LC50 (96 hour), given in -log(mol/l) and its conversion in mg/L. It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/
            The model is a re-implementation of the original model developed by Todd Martin inside T.E.S.T. software for US EPA. The T.E.S.T. software is freely available at:
            http://www.epa.gov/nrmrl/std/cppb/qsar/.</Description>
        <Model>The model is a linear regression made on 21 molecular descriptors. The regression coefficients have been calculated on the T.E.S.T. original dataset, that contains 816 compounds extracted from the ECOTOX aquatic toxicity database (http://cfpub.epa.gov/ecotox/), splitted in 652 compounds for the training set and 164 for the test set. More details on the model can be found in the T.E.S.T. documentation: http://www.epa.gov/nrmrl/std/cppb/qsar/testuserguide.pdf</Model>
        <Descriptors>The descriptors used are the following:
            - SsssN: Sum of >N- E-States
            - SdssS_acnt: Count of =S&lt;
            - MDEC33: Molecular distance edge between all tertiary carbons
            - MDEO11: Molecular distance edge between all primary oxygens
            - BEHm2: Highest eigenvalue n. 2 of Burden matrix / weighted by atomic masses
            - nDB: Number of double bonds
            - nS: Number of Sulfur atoms
            - nR09: Number of 9-membered rings
            - ATS5p: Broto-Moreau autocorrelation of a topological structure - lag 5 / weighted by atomic
            polarizabilities
            - MATS7e: Moran autocorrelation - lag 7 / weighted by atomic Sanderson electronegativities
            - GATS3e: Geary autocorrelation - lag 3 / weighted by atomic Sanderson electronegativities
            - SRW03: Self-returning walk count of order 3
            - ALOGP: Ghose-Crippen octanol water coefficient
            - NO2 [aromatic attach]: -NO2 [aromatic attach] fragment count
            - CHO [aliphatic attach]: -CHO [aliphatic attach] fragment count
            - OH [phosphorus attach]: -OH [phosphorus attach] fragment count
            - >NN=O: >NN=O fragment count
            - C(=O)- [2 nitrogen attach]: -C(=O)- [2 nitrogen attach] fragment count
            - C#N [aliphatic attach]: -C#N [aliphatic attach] fragment count
            - Cl [olefinic attach]: -Cl [olefinic attach] fragment count
            - CHO [aromatic attach]: -CHO [aromatic attach] fragment count
            The descriptors are entirely calculated by an in-house software module in which they are implemented as described in: R. Todeschini and V. Consonni, Molecular Descriptors for Chemoinformatics, Wiley-VCH, 2009. The original code for descriptors calculation has been kindly provided by Todd Martin.</Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 => index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>652.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.69</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.83</RMSE_Train>
        <n_Test>164.0</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.627</R2_Test>
        <RMSE_Test>0.889</RMSE_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>

</xml>