<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE QMRF PUBLIC "http://qmrf.sourceforge.net/qmrf.dtd" "qmrf.dtd">
<QMRF author="" contact="J" date="" email="" name="(Q)SAR Model Reporting Format" schema_version="1.0" url="" version="">
<QMRF_chapters>

<QSAR_identifier chapter="1"  help="" name="QSAR identifier">
<QSAR_title chapter="1.1"  help="" name="QSAR identifier (title)">
VEGA Carcinogenicity model (IRFMN/Antares) (version 1.0.1)
</QSAR_title>
<QSAR_models chapter="1.2"  help="" name="Other related models">
A related model is the E(expert)model, that uses a different specie for the carcinogenesis learning set; it is described in the publication:
Azadi Golbamaki, Emilio Benfenati, Nazanin Golbamaki, Alberto Manganaro, Erinc Merdivan, Alessandra Roncaglioni &amp; Giuseppina Gini (2016) New clues on carcinogenicity-related substructures derived from mining two large datasets of chemical compounds, Journal of Environmental Science and Health, Part C, 34:2, 97-113, DOI: 10.1080/10590501.2016.1166879
</QSAR_models>
<QSAR_software chapter="1.3"  help="" name="Software coding the model">
VEGA (https://www.vegahub.eu/)
The VEGA software provides QSAR models to predict tox, ecotox, environ, phys-chem and toxicokinetic properties of chemical substances.
emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it
</QSAR_software>
</QSAR_identifier>

<QSAR_General_information chapter="2"  help="" name="General information">
<qmrf_date chapter="2.1"  help="" name="Date of QMRF">
7-02-2022
</qmrf_date>
<qmrf_authors chapter="2.2"  help="" name="QMRF author(s) and contact details">
[1] Alessio Gamba Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy alessio.gamba@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
[2] Emilio Benfenati Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
</qmrf_authors>
<qmrf_date_revision chapter="2.3"  help="" name="Date of QMRF update(s)">
NA
</qmrf_date_revision>
<qmrf_revision chapter="2.4"  help="" name="QMRF update(s)">
NA
</qmrf_revision>
<model_authors chapter="2.5"  help="" name="Model developer(s) and contact details">
[1] Azadi Golbamaki Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy azadi.golbamaki@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
[2] Emilio Benfenati Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
[3] Nazanin Golbamaki Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy https://www.marionegri.it/
[4] Alberto Manganaro RCCS-Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri Via La Masa 19, 20156 Milano, Italy alberto.manganaro@marionegri.it
[5] Erinc Merdivan Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy https://www.marionegri.it/
[6] Alessandra Roncaglioni Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy alessandra.roncaglioni@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/

[7] Giuseppina Gini Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy https://www.marionegri.it/
</model_authors>
<model_date chapter="2.6"  help="" name="Date of model development and/or publication">
2016
</model_date>
<references chapter="2.7"  help="" name="Reference(s) to main scientific papers and/or software package">
[1] Azadi Golbamaki, Emilio Benfenati, Nazanin Golbamaki, Alberto Manganaro, Erinc Merdivan, Alessandra Roncaglioni &amp; Giuseppina Gini (2016) New clues on carcinogenicity-related substructures derived from mining two large datasets of chemical compounds, Journal of Environmental Science and Health, Part C, 34:2, 97-113 
[2] Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G. VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology 
Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy 
Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107
</references>
<info_availability chapter="2.8"  help="" name="Availability of information about the model">
The model is non-proprietary and the training set is available.
</info_availability>
<related_models chapter="2.9"  help="" name="Availability of another QMRF for exactly the same model">
Another QMRF is not available.
</related_models>
</QSAR_General_information>

<QSAR_Endpoint chapter="3"  help="" name="Defining the endpoint - OECD Principle 1">
<model_species chapter="3.1"  help="" name="Species">
Male and/or female rat
</model_species>
<model_endpoint chapter="3.2"  help="" name="Endpoint">
TOX 7.7. Carcinogenicity (in vivo)
</model_endpoint>
<endpoint_comments chapter="3.3"  help="" name="Comment on endpoint">
The dataset is based on the classification based on TD50 (which is the dose that produces an
increase of 50% of the tumors in animals) value for rat; the label carcinogen is if TD50 is positive, otherwise is not carcinogen
</endpoint_comments>
<endpoint_units chapter="3.4"  help="" name="Endpoint units">
TD(50) (daily dose rate in mg/kg body weight/day to induce tumors in half of test animals that would have remained tumor/free at zero dose), is estimated for each tissue-tumor combination report
</endpoint_units>
<endpoint_variable chapter="3.5"  help="" name="Dependent variable">
The dependent variable is cancerogenic effect, as binary classification: 0 (non-carcinogen), 1 (carcinogen)
For each carcinogen compounds a value of TD50 is associated; for each non-carcinogen compounds there is not a value of TD50
</endpoint_variable>
<endpoint_protocol chapter="3.6"  help="" name="Experimental protocol">
All the TD50 values were derived from the Carcinogenic Potency DataBase: Lois Gold’s Carcinogenic Potency Database (CPDB).University of California, http://potency.berkeley.edu. 2011; original publication: https://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/doi/pdf/10.1289/ehp.84589
An assignment of carcinogenic categorical activity based on evidence for or against activity within the species group in Target Sites of Rats (Male, Female or Both) as provided in the CPDB Summary Table. Hence, “active” or positive (P) or carcinogen was assigned for a compound if one or more TD50 and the tumor site are listed for one or more rat carcinogenicity sex/species cell (rat male, rat female, rat both) and “inactive” or not positive (NP) or non carcinogens was assigned for a compound if no TD50 or tumor site are listed and one or more “no positive results” entry for one or more rat carcinogenicity sex/species cell, i.e. one or more experiments are reported in the CPDB for species, but none are positive. In other words, chemicals were classified as not carcinogenic when the results obtained during all animal tests on rats were assigned as not positive (NP) (or not active) and contrary, compounds were classified as positive (P) (or active) when any of the in vivo assays gave a well-defined TD50 value.
</endpoint_protocol>
<endpoint_data_quality chapter="3.7"  help="" name="Endpoint data quality and variability">
Briefly the 1543 mono-constituent organic compounds in ANTARES merge the compounds from the EU-funded project CAESAR dataset (derived from Distributed Structure-Searchable Toxicity DSSTox database, which was built from the Lois Gold’s Carcinogenic Potency Database) and the “FDA 2009 SAR Carcinogenicity—SAR Structures” database.
ANTARES Database sources: [3] Fjodorova, N., Vračko, M., Novič, M. et al. New public QSAR model for carcinogenicity. Chemistry Central Journal 4, S3 (2010). https://doi.org/10.1186/1752-153X-4-S1-S3
</endpoint_data_quality>
</QSAR_Endpoint>

<QSAR_Algorithm chapter="4"  help="" name="Defining the algorithm - OECD Principle 2">
<algorithm_type chapter="4.1"  help="" name="Type of model">
it is based of collection of carcinogenic potential fragments; the model has been built as a set of rules, extracted with Sarpy software from a dataset obtained from the carcinogenicity database of EU-funded project ANTARES. This database is a collection of chemical rat carcinogenesis data (presence of carcinogenic effects in male or female rats) obtained from the CAESAR project database and the “FDA 2009 SAR Carcinogenicity - SAR Structures” database. 
The CAESAR toxicity values originated from the distributed structure-searchable toxicity DSSTox database, which was built from the Lois Gold’s carcinogenic potency database (CPDB).
The Sarpy software has been used with a cross-validated procedure ending with the extraction of a set of 127 rules (structural alerts) related to carcinogenic activity. These rules are expressed SMARTS representing molecular fragments.
If at least one rule is matching with the given compound, a “Carcinogen” prediction is given. Otherwise, “Possible NON-Carcinogen” prediction is given
</algorithm_type>
<algorithm_explicit chapter="4.2"  help="" name="Explicit algorithm">
Classification model.
The algorithm generates molecular substructures of arbitrary complexity, and the fragment candidates to become SAs are automatically selected on the basis of their prediction performance in a learning set.
The output of SARpy consists in a set of rules in the form: IF contains THEN the script is described in the publication: Ferrari T, Gini G, Bakhtyari NG, Benfenati E. Mining toxicity structural alerts from SMILES: A new way to derive Structure Activity Relationships. In: Computational Intelligence and Data Mining (CIDM), IEEE Symposium on: 11–15 April 2011: 120–127 
</algorithm_explicit>
<algorithms_descriptors chapter="4.3"  help="" name="Descriptors in the model">
Here the list of the 127 new SA found:
SA 1: CN[N+]=O 
SA 2: NNC=O 
SA 3: CN(C=O)N=O 
SA 4: CCCCCCN(C)N=O 
SA 5: CCCN(CCC)N=O 
SA 6: CNCCNN=O 
SA 7: CNCCN(C)N=O 
SA 8: CCNN=O 
SA 9: CCCCCN(C)N=O 
SA 10: CCCCN(C)N=O 
SA 11: CC(O)CNN=O 
SA 12: CN(N=O)C(=O)NCCO 
SA 13: NC(=O)N(CCO)N=O 
SA 14: CN(N=O)C(N)=O 
SA 15: CCCNN=O 
SA 16: O(c1ccccc1)c2ccccc2 
SA 17: COc1cccc(O)c1 
SA 18: CCc1ccc(OC)cc1O 
SA 19: CCCNCNN=O 
SA 20: CCOC(=O)C(C)(C)O 
SA 21: CC(C)(O)C(O)=O 
SA 22: Cc1ccccc1-c2ccc(N)cc2 
SA 23: Nc1ccc(cc1)-c2ccc(N)cc2
SA 24: Nc1ccc(cc1)-c2ccccc2 
SA 25: Nc1ccc(C=C)cc1 4 SA 
26: Nc1cccc(c1)-c2ccccc2 
SA 27: Cc1ccc(N)c(C)c1 
SA 28: Cc1ccccc1N 
SA 29: Nc1ccc(Cc2ccc(N)cc2)cc1 
SA 30: CN(C)c1ccc(Cc2ccccc2)cc1 
SA 31: Cc1ccc(N)cc1 
SA 32: Cc1ccc(NO)cc1 
SA 33: Cc1cccc(N)c1 
SA 34: CNc1ccc(C=C)cc1 
SA 35: Nc1ccc2ccccc2c1 
SA 36: CNc1ccc(N)cc1 
SA 37: Nc1ccccc1O 
SA 38: COc1ccccc1N 
SA 39: Oc1cccc2ccccc12 
SA 40: Nc1ccc(O)c(N)c1 
SA 41: CC(C)C(C)(O)CO 
SA 42: Nc1cccc(c1)S(O)(=O)=O 
SA 43: Cc1cccc2ccccc12 
SA 44: NNCO 
SA 45: CN(N)CO 
SA 46: CC(O)CNN 
SA 47: NNCCO 
SA 48: NNc1ccccc1 
SA 49: NNCC=C 
SA 50: CCNN 
SA 51: CCCNN 
SA 52: CC(=O)NN 
SA 53: CCCN(N)CCC 
SA 54: CCCN(C)N 
SA 55: NN 
SA 56: ClCCCl 
SA 57: CCl 
SA 58: CCBr 
SA 59: CBr 
SA 60: c1ccc2cc3c(ccc4ccccc34)cc2c1 
SA 61: c1ccc-2c(c1)-c3cccc4cccc-2c34 
SA 62: CN=O SA 
63: N=O SA 
64: NO 
SA 65: Oc1cccc(c1)-c2cccc(O)c2 
SA 66: OS(O)(=O)=O 
SA 67: COS(O)=O 
SA 68: COS(=O)=O 
SA 69: ClC1CCCC(Cl)C1Cl 
SA 70: CC(Cl)CCCCCl 
SA 71: c1ccc(cc1)N=Nc2ccccc2
SA 72: CCNCCCl 5 
SA 73: ClCCNCCCl 
SA 74: Cc1ccncn1 
SA 75: c1cncnc1 
SA 76: CC(=C)C(O)=O 
SA 77: CC=C(C)CO 
SA 78: CC(C)=NO 
SA 79: CC(C)=N 
SA 80: Cn1cncn1 
SA 81: c1ncnn1 
SA 82: COc1ccc(CC=C)cc1 
SA 83: Nc1ncc2ncn(CCCCO)c2n1 
SA 84: OCC1OC(CC1O)n2cnc3cncnc23 
SA 85: CC1CCC=C(C)C1 
SA 86: C1C=CCC=C1 
SA 87: O=C(OCc1ccccc1)c2ccccc2 
SA 88: CCOCc1ccccc1C 
SA 89: C(=Cc1ccccc1)c2ccccc2 
SA 90: [O-][N+](=O)c1ccco1 
SA 91: CCNCC(C)=O 
SA 92: N=[N+] 
SA 93: Cc1ccc(cc1)S(O)(=O)=O 
SA 94: O=C1c2ccccc2C(=O)c3ccccc13 
SA 95: Cc1cccnc1 
SA 96: CCCCC(O)CCCCC(O)CCC 
SA 97: Clc1cccc(Cl)c1Cl 
SA 98: COP=O 
SA 99: CC(CN)c1ccccc1 
SA 100: OCC#C 
SA 101: NNCc1ccccc1 
SA 102: C1CCc2ccccc2C1 
SA 103: c1ccsc1 
SA 104: Nc1ccccn1 
SA 105: C1CO1 
SA 106: CC(O)CCCC=O 
SA 107: C[S]=O 
SA 108:c1cscn1 
SA 109: CC1COCO1 
SA 110: Nc1ccc([S]c2ccccc2)cc1 
SA 111: Cc1ccc(cc1)C(N)=O 
SA 112: CN(C)P(N(C)C)N(C)C 
SA 113: [N+]c1cncn1 
SA 114: O=C1CCO1 
SA 115: OCCNCC=C 
SA 116: CCNCCCC(C)C 
SA 117: c1ccoc1 
SA 118: CCOC(N)=O 
SA 119: C=CCCCCC=O 6 
SA 120: C1CN1 
SA 121: c1cc2ccccc2s1 
SA 122: Cc1ncc[nH]1 
SA 123: [O-][N+](=O)c1ccc(o1)-c2cscn2 
SA 124: C#C 
SA 125: CCF 
SA 126: CN=[N+] 
SA 127: CCCN=CN
</algorithms_descriptors>
<descriptors_selection chapter="4.4"  help="" name="Descriptor selection">
The SARpy software has been used with a cross-validated procedure (described in details in the paper), ending with the extraction of a set of 127 rules (structural alerts) related to carcinogenic activity.
These rules are expressed SMARTS representing molecular fragments.
If at least one rule is matching with the given compound, a “Carcinogen” prediction is given. Otherwise, “Possible NON-Carcinogen” prediction is given using the SARpy software, each chemical in the learning set was fragmented in silico into all possible fragments meeting user-specified criteria. For this study we
extracted only the “ACTIVE” fragments (or SAs) and the default values for the minimum and maximum number of atoms in a fragment were set for the fragment extractions of each model (minimum = 2; maximum = 18). Another configuration to establish by the user is the minimum number of compounds in the learning set in which an active (or inactive) fragment is found. In our analysis, the minimum number of compounds that contain a potential active fragment was set to three. Conventionally, in this study we call this model R.
</descriptors_selection>
<descriptors_generation chapter="4.5"  help="" name="Algorithm and descriptor generation">
The SAR in Python (SARpy) program is a Python script based on the OpenBabel chemical library. SARpy creates classification models by using categorized active and inactive chemicals in a learning set to identify molecular fragments that are associated with a particular biological, pharmaceutical, or toxicological activity. The algorithm generates molecular substructures of arbitrary complexity, and the fragments candidates to become SAs are automatically selected on the basis of their prediction performance in a learning set. The output of SARpy consists in a set of rules in the form: IF contains THEN, where the SA is expressed as  SMARTS string, for use by human experts or other chemical software.SMARTS notations are text representations of substructures that allow specification of wildcard atoms and bonds,which can be used to formulate substructure queries for a chemical database.Those rules can be used as a predictive model simply by calling a SMARTS matching program. For the matching phase, SMILES and the SMARTS strings are translated into graphs and the two graphs are compared to each other.
</descriptors_generation>
<descriptors_generation_software chapter="4.6"  help="" name="Software name and version for descriptor generation">
SARpy
VEGA
https://www.vegahub.eu
https://www.vegahub.eu/portfolio-item/sarpy/
</descriptors_generation_software>
<descriptors_chemicals_ratio chapter="4.7"  help="" name="Chemicals/Descriptors ratio">
NA
</descriptors_chemicals_ratio>
</QSAR_Algorithm>

<QSAR_Applicability_domain chapter="5"  help="" name="Defining the applicability domain - OECD Principle 3">
<app_domain_description chapter="5.1"  help="" name="Description of the applicability domain of the model">
The Applicability Domain (AD) is assessed using the original algorithm implemented within VEGA. An overall AD index is calculated, based on a number of parameters, which relate to the results obtained on similar chemicals within the training and test sets.
If  1 ≥ AD index &amp;gt; 0.8, the predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model. It corresponds to good reliability of prediction.
If  0.8 ≥ AD index &amp;gt; 0.6, the predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model. It corresponds to moderate reliability of prediction.
If AD index ≤ 0.6, the predicted substance is out of the Applicability Domain of the model and corresponds to low reliability of prediction. 

Indices are calculated on the first k = 3 most similar molecules, each having Sk similarity value with the target molecule. 

Similarity index (IdxSimilarity) is calculated as:

[img src="/data/carc_antares/fig_sim_class.png"]

where Diam is the difference in similarity values between the most similar molecule and the k-th molecule.

Accuracy index (IdxAccuracy) is calculated as:

[img src="/data/carc_antares/fig_acc_conc_class.png"]

where the molecules with c index are the subset of the k molecules where the prediction of the model matches with the experimental value of the molecule.

Concordance index (IdxConcordance) is calculated as:

[img src="/data/carc_antares/fig_acc_conc_class.png"]

where the molecules with c index are the subset of the k molecules where the experimental value of the molecule matches with the prediction made for the target molecule.

ACF contribution (IdxACF) index is calculated as

[img src="/data/carc_antares/fig_acf.png"]

where: rare is calculated on the number of fragments found in the molecule and found in the training set in less than 3 occurences as following: if the number is 0, rare is set to 1.0; if the number is 1, rare is set to 0.6; otherwise rare is set to 0.4

missing is calculated on the number of fragments found in the molecule and never found in the training set as following: if the number is 0, missing is set to 1.0; if the number is 1, missing is set to 0.6; otherwise missing is set to 0.4

AD final index is calculated as following:

[img src="/img/fig_ad.png"]
</app_domain_description>
<app_domain_method chapter="5.2"  help="" name="Method used to assess the applicability domain">
The Applicability Domain and chemical similarity is measured with the algorithm developed for VEGA. Full details are in the VEGA website (www.vegahub.eu), including the open access paper describing it [5]. The AD also evaluates the correctness of the prediction on similar compounds (accuracy), the consistency between the predicted value for the target compound and the experimental values of the similar compounds, the range of the descriptors, and the presence of unusual fragments, using atom centred fragments.
This description briefly mentions the different types of indices (Similarity index, Accuracy index, Concordance index, Descriptors range check, ACF (Atom Centered Fragments) index, Pos/Non-Pos difference and Neurons concordance) that are embedded in the global AD index, as fully explained in the guide of the model
</app_domain_method>
<app_domain_software chapter="5.3"  help="" name="Software name and version for applicability domain assessment">
VEGA
Included in the VEGA software and automatically displayed when running the model
emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it
https://www.vegahub.eu/
</app_domain_software>
<applicability_limits chapter="5.4"  help="" name="Limits of applicability">
The model is not applicable to inorganic chemicals and substances containing unusual elements (i.e., different from C, O, N, S, P, Cl, Br, F, I). Salts can be predicted only if converted to the neutralized form.
</applicability_limits>
</QSAR_Applicability_domain>

<QSAR_Robustness chapter="6"  help="" name="Internal validation - OECD Principle 4">
<training_set_availability chapter="6.1"  help="" name="Availability of the training set">
Part of training set is proprietary 
</training_set_availability>
<training_set_data chapter="6.2"  help="" name="Available information for the training set">
CAS RN: Yes
Chemical Name: Yes
Smiles: Yes
Formula: No
INChI: No
MOL file: No
NanoMaterial: No
</training_set_data>
<training_set_descriptors chapter="6.3"  help="" name="Data for each descriptor variable for the training set">
All
</training_set_descriptors>
<dependent_var_availability chapter="6.4"  help="" name="Data for the dependent variable for the training set">
All
</dependent_var_availability>
<other_info chapter="6.5"  help="" name="Other information about the training set">
The ANTAREs’ carcinogenicity database is a collection of chemical rat carcinogenesis data (presence of carcinogenic effects in male or female rats) obtained from the EU-funded project CAESAR dataset and the “FDA 2009 SAR Carcinogenicity—SAR Structures” database. The CAESAR toxicity values were originated from the Distributed Structure-Searchable Toxicity DSSTox database, which was built from the Lois Gold’s Carcinogenic Potency Database. The compounds with a definite TD50 (which is the dose that produces an increase of 50% of the tumors in animals) value for rat in this dataset were labeled as carcinogenic, while the remaining were labeled as non-carcinogenic. Additional 738 chemicals different from the 805 CAESAR compounds were added. The added chemicals are from the “FDA2009SARCarcinogenicity— SARStructures” database using the Leadscope database. Here a categorical label for carcinogenicity was already contained in the original dataset and again the compound was labeled as carcinogenic if a positive outcome was detected in male or female rats. So, a total number of 1543 compounds (784 positive substances and 760 negative substances) constituted the ANTARES dataset.
</other_info>
<preprocessing chapter="6.6"  help="" name="Pre-processing of data before modelling">
NA
</preprocessing>
<goodness_of_fit chapter="6.7"  help="" name="Statistics for goodness-of-fit">
Statistics recalculated running the model on VEGA with the training set:
FN:139 ; FP:392 ; TN: 645;TP 368 ; Accuracy 0,66: Specificity 0,48;
Sensitivity 0.83; MCC 0.34
</goodness_of_fit>
<loo chapter="6.8"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by leave-one-out cross-validation">
NA
</loo>
<lmo chapter="6.9"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by leave-many-out cross-validation">
778 compound LMO cross-validation using five rule sets extracted from the ANTARES dataset gave an average of 71% accuracy,73% sensitivity and 69% specificity
</lmo>
<yscrambling chapter="6.10"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by Y-scrambling">
NA
</yscrambling>
<bootstrap chapter="6.11"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by bootstrap">
NA
</bootstrap>
<other_statistics chapter="6.12"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by other methods">
NA
</other_statistics>
</QSAR_Robustness>

<QSAR_Predictivity chapter="7"  help="" name="External validation - OECD Principle 4">
<validation_set_availability chapter="7.1"  help="" name="Availability of the external validation set">
Part of test set is proprietary 
</validation_set_availability>
<validation_set_data chapter="7.2"  help="" name="Available information for the external validation set">
CAS RN: Yes
Chemical Name: Yes
Smiles: Yes
Formula: No
INChI: No
MOL file: No
NanoMaterial: No
</validation_set_data>
<validation_set_descriptors chapter="7.3"  help="" name="Data for each descriptor variable for the external validation set">
All
</validation_set_descriptors>
<validation_dependent_var_availability chapter="7.4"  help="" name="Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set">
All
</validation_dependent_var_availability>
<validation_other_info chapter="7.5"  help="" name="Other information about the external validation set">
The external validation set is prepared from eChemPortal inventory.It is composed by 258 total mono-constituent organics 
</validation_other_info>
<experimental_design chapter="7.6"  help="" name="Experimental design of test set">
The following queries were done to extract the data. 
• Study result type: experimental result 
• Reliability: 1 and 2 
• Species: mouse and rat
• Maximum number of studies: 4
The second query consisted of: 
• Study result type: experimental result
• Reliability:1 and 2 
• Species: mouse and/or rat 
• Sources: any guideline and exposure route
The list resulted from the first query comprised 308 compounds, whereas the second query returned a list of 166 compounds, which were mostly in common with the results of the first query.
The studies conducted for the first list of compounds have been manually evaluated. Afterward, Classification Labelling and Packaging (CLP) inventory was checked for the positive (i.e., carcinogenic) chemicals collected by the previous queries.
Inside the CLP inventory 68 compounds already present in the data collection have been found, this confirmed the carcinogenic properties.
In the dataset there are 64 positive compounds,169 negative compounds and 90 equivocal compounds. The equivocal results are due to the presence of conflicting information in different sources or different studies in the same source. It should be noticed that for already classified compounds (no conflicting information), the level of uncertainty in the assignment is not homogeneous, because some of the compounds were classified on the basis of a single study (i.e., data present in one single source). In the data collected 49 positive compounds were identified in our dataset as positives. Fifty-seven negative compounds are non-carcinogenic in both lists and are not present in the list of compounds retrieved from the CL P inventory. Sixty-four compounds are considered as non-carcinogens because of the presence of only one single study in the two lists.
</experimental_design>
<validation_predictivity chapter="7.7"  help="" name="Predictivity - Statistics obtained by external validation">
accuracy: 63% ,sensitivity: 63%, specificity 62%
These statistics refer to the original version of the model [1], not to that implemented in VEGA.
The most recent model version has been internally validated using a further external validation set (merging the datasets of the VEGA models: Carcinogenicity model (CAESAR) and Carcinogenicity model (IRFMN-ISSCAN-CGX).
After eliminating duplicates, the additional external dataset counted 267 compounds.
Statistics considering ADI thresholds:

63 compounds in the AD, AD index &amp;gt; 0.8
Sensitivity=	89%, Specificity= 75%, Accuracy= 86% and MCC= 0.63
TP	42, TN	12, FP	4, FN	5.

91 compounds could be out the AD, 0.8 ≥ AD index &amp;gt; 0.6
Sensitivity= 83%, Specificity= 68%, Accuracy= 79% and MCC=0.50
TP	55, TN	17, FP	8, FN	11.

113 compounds out of the AD, AD index ≤ 0.6
Sensitivity=	73%, Specificity= 29%, Accuracy= 59% and MCC= 0.02
TP	57, TN	10, FP	25, FN	21.
</validation_predictivity>
<validation_assessment chapter="7.8"  help="" name="Predictivity - Assessment of the external validation set">
NA
</validation_assessment>
<validation_comments chapter="7.9"  help="" name="Comments on the external validation of the model">
NA
</validation_comments>
</QSAR_Predictivity>

<QSAR_Interpretation chapter="8"  help="" name="Providing a mechanistic interpretation - OECD Principle 5">
<mechanistic_basis chapter="8.1"  help="" name="Mechanistic basis of the model">
NA
</mechanistic_basis>
<mechanistic_basis_comments chapter="8.2"  help="" name="A priori or a posteriori mechanistic interpretation">
NA
</mechanistic_basis_comments>
<mechanistic_basis_info chapter="8.3"  help="" name="Other information about the mechanistic interpretation">
NA
</mechanistic_basis_info>
</QSAR_Interpretation>

<QSAR_Miscelaneous chapter="9"  help="" name="Miscellaneous information">
<comments chapter="9.1"  help="" name="Comments">
NA
</comments>
<bibliography chapter="9.2"  help="" name="Bibliography">
[1] Azadi Golbamaki, Emilio Benfenati, Nazanin Golbamaki, Alberto Manganaro, Erinc Merdivan, Alessandra Roncaglioni &amp; Giuseppina Gini (2016) New clues on carcinogenicity-related substructures derived from mining two large datasets of chemical compounds, Journal of Environmental Science and Health, Part C, 34:2, 97-113
[2] Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G. VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology 
Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy 
Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107
[3] Fjodorova, N., Vračko, M., Novič, M. et al. New public QSAR model for carcinogenicity. Chemistry Central Journal 4, S3 (2010). https://doi.org/10.1186/1752-153X-4-S1-S3
[4] Ferrari T, Gini G, Bakhtyari NG, Benfenati E. Mining toxicity structural alerts from SMILES: A new way to derive Structure Activity Relationships. In: Computational Intelligence and Data Mining (CIDM), IEEE Symposium on: 11–15 April 2011: 120–127
[5] Floris, M., Manganaro, A., Nicolotti, O. et al. A generalizable definition of chemical similarity for read-across. J Cheminform 6, 39 (2014). https://doi.org/10.1186/s13321-014-0039-1
</bibliography>
<attachments chapter="9.3"  help="" name="Supporting information">
Training set(s)Test set(s)Supporting information:
All available dataset are present in the model inside the VEGA software.
</attachments>
</QSAR_Miscelaneous>


</QMRF_chapters>
</QMRF>