<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE QMRF PUBLIC "http://qmrf.sourceforge.net/qmrf.dtd" "qmrf.dtd">
<QMRF author="" contact="J" date="" email="" name="(Q)SAR Model Reporting Format" schema_version="1.0" url="" version="">
<QMRF_chapters>

<QSAR_identifier chapter="1"  help="" name="QSAR identifier">
<QSAR_title chapter="1.1"  help="" name="QSAR identifier (title)">
Algae Acute (EC50) Toxicity model (IRFMN) - v 1.0.1
</QSAR_title>
<QSAR_models chapter="1.2"  help="" name="Other related models">
Algae: EC50 72h (specific growth rate)
Algae: NOEC 72h (specific growth rate)
Daphnia magna: EC50 48h, acute (immobilisation)
Daphnia magna: NOEC 21d, chronic (reproduction)
Fish (Oryzias latipes): LC50 96h, acute (mortality)
Fish (Oryzias latipes): NOEC, chronic (ELS-test).
</QSAR_models>
<QSAR_software chapter="1.3"  help="" name="Software coding the model">
VEGA (https://www.vegahub.eu/)
The VEGA software provides QSAR models to predict tox, ecotox, environ, phys-chem and toxicokinetic properties of chemical substances.
emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it
</QSAR_software>
</QSAR_identifier>

<QSAR_General_information chapter="2"  help="" name="General information">
<qmrf_date chapter="2.1"  help="" name="Date of QMRF">
26-03-2021
</qmrf_date>
<qmrf_authors chapter="2.2"  help="" name="QMRF author(s) and contact details">
[1] Alessio Gamba Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy alessio.gamba@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
[2] Emilio Benfenati Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
</qmrf_authors>
<qmrf_date_revision chapter="2.3"  help="" name="Date of QMRF update(s)">
NA
</qmrf_date_revision>
<qmrf_revision chapter="2.4"  help="" name="QMRF update(s)">
NA
</qmrf_revision>
<model_authors chapter="2.5"  help="" name="Model developer(s) and contact details">
[1] Emilio Benfenati Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
[2] Alberto Manganaro Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy alberto.manganaro@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
</model_authors>
<model_date chapter="2.6"  help="" name="Date of model development and/or publication">
The model was developed in 2019.
</model_date>
<references chapter="2.7"  help="" name="Reference(s) to main scientific papers and/or software package">
[1] Toma, C.; Cappelli, C. I.; Manganaro, A.; Lombardo, A.; Arning, J.; Benfenati, E. New Models to Predict the Acute and Chronic Toxicities of Representative Species of the Main Trophic Levels of Aquatic Environments. Molecules 2021, 26 (22), 6983. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26226983.
[2] Benfenati E, Roncaglioni A, Lombardo A, Manganaro A. Integrating QSAR, Read-Across, and Screening Tools: The VEGAHUB Platform as an Example. Advances in Computational Toxicology; Springer; 2019. p. 365-81.
[3] Chemistry Development Kit (CDK) http://sourceforge.net/apps/mediawiki/cdk/index.php?title=Main_Page
</references>
<info_availability chapter="2.8"  help="" name="Availability of information about the model">
The model is non-proprietary and the training set is available.
</info_availability>
<related_models chapter="2.9"  help="" name="Availability of another QMRF for exactly the same model">
Another QMRF is not available.
</related_models>
</QSAR_General_information>

<QSAR_Endpoint chapter="3"  help="" name="Defining the endpoint - OECD Principle 1">
<model_species chapter="3.1"  help="" name="Species">
Rhapidocelis subcapitata, previously named as Selenastrum capricornutum or Pseudokirchneriella subcapitata (as reported in the original dataset)
</model_species>
<model_endpoint chapter="3.2"  help="" name="Endpoint">
ECOTOX 6.1.5. Long-term toxicity to aquatic algae and cyanobacteria C.f. OECD TG 201 Freshwater Alga and Cyanobacteria, Growth Inhibition Test
</model_endpoint>
<endpoint_comments chapter="3.3"  help="" name="Comment on endpoint">
This test evaluates the effects of a substance on the growth of freshwater microalgae. Exponentially growing test algae under optimal temperature and light conditions are exposed to the test substance in batch cultures. The biological effects are the reduction of growth in a series of algal cultures exposed to, at least, five concentrations of a test substance. The response variable is the reduction of the average specific growth rate ( = calculated on the basis of the logarithmic increase of biomass during the test period, expressed per day)  as a function of the exposure concentration within the exponential growth phase of the control cultures over a period of normally 72 hours (c.f. also OECD TG (2011) paragraph 46-52)  From the average specific growth rates recorded in a series of test solutions, the concentration bringing about a specified x % inhibition of growth rate (e.g. 50%) is determined and expressed as the ErCx (e.g. ErC50). 
Slight modification of the OECD Test No. 201 ( 2011, 2006 &amp; 1984): Freshwater   Alga and Cyanobacteria, Growth Inhibition Test, OECD Guidelines for the Testing  of  Chemicals,  Section  2,  Éditions  OCDE,  Paris, All tests were performed according to OECD 201 and GLP but some tests performed before 2002 employed dispersants. In a few cases where the control cultures specific growth rate had decreased at 72 hrs the specific growth rate was in accordance with OECD TG 201 calculated based on the growth until 48 hrs. https://doi.org/10.1787/9789264069923-en.
</endpoint_comments>
<endpoint_units chapter="3.4"  help="" name="Endpoint units">
72h ErC50, expressed in mg/L
</endpoint_units>
<endpoint_variable chapter="3.5"  help="" name="Dependent variable">
	NA
</endpoint_variable>
<endpoint_protocol chapter="3.6"  help="" name="Experimental protocol">
OECD TG 201 (2011,2006 and 1984) 
</endpoint_protocol>
<endpoint_data_quality chapter="3.7"  help="" name="Endpoint data quality and variability">
The QSAR model is based on a dataset from the Japanese Ministry of Environment including experimental toxicity values from short- and long-term aquatic toxicity tests https://www.env.go.jp/en/chemi/sesaku/aquatic_Mar_2016.pdf. These data were obtained according to the OECD TG 201  and GLP. All tests were performed according to OECD 201 and GLP but some tests performed before 2002 employed dispersants. In a few cases where the control cultures specific growth rate had decreased at 72 hrs the specific growth rate was in accordance with OECD TG 201 calculated based on the growth until 48 hrs.
</endpoint_data_quality>
</QSAR_Endpoint>

<QSAR_Algorithm chapter="4"  help="" name="Defining the algorithm - OECD Principle 2">
<algorithm_type chapter="4.1"  help="" name="Type of model">
The model is based on 315 experimental data on algae acute toxicity (ErC50, 72h growth rate) retrieved from the Japanese Ministry of Environment (http://www.env.go.jp/en/chemi/sesaku/aquatic_Mar_2016.pd                         f. The model is developed based on a Tree Ensemble Random Forest.
</algorithm_type>
<algorithm_explicit chapter="4.2"  help="" name="Explicit algorithm">
Tree Ensemble Random Forest
To derive the models, we divided the data in training and test sets with the ratio of 80:20. In order to obtain a uniform distribution of the endpoint values between the two subsets we applied an activity and descriptors sampling method. We performed a Principal Component Analysis (PCA) on all the descriptors and we selected the first two principal components. We selected five random compounds, and then we picked the most dissimilar compound from the sample pool according to the first two principal components and the response using several combinations of distance metrics and scoring functions. Then we added the compound to the pool repeating the operation until we reached the desired number for the training set.
Among the several algorithms used, we obtained the best results in terms of performance with a Random Forest called Tree ensemble. Tree ensemble builds a series of regression trees with different rows and different variables (according to certain parameters) and then it aggregates the results as an ensemble of models. It chooses the parameters for the variables of each tree and the number of compounds evaluating the performance of several models (Hyperparameter tuning Research) using as metric R2 of a Bootstrap (100 iterations) cross-validation on training set.
</algorithm_explicit>
<algorithms_descriptors chapter="4.3"  help="" name="Descriptors in the model">
 NA
</algorithms_descriptors>
<descriptors_selection chapter="4.4"  help="" name="Descriptor selection">
Dragon 7.0 extension for KNIME has been used to calculate the descriptors, resulting in 3839 2D descriptors. Then we applied a pruning process both to the compounds and to the descriptors pools. Firstly, we removed the compounds for which it was not feasible to calculate AlogP (octanol-water partition coefficient (Ghose and Crippen, 1986; Viswanadhan et al., 1993; Ghose et al., 1998)), as it is generally well acknowledged that this descriptor is the most correlated to the response. Then, to reduce the great number of variables, we removed all the descriptors with constant values (var(X) = 0), or which correlate over 0.95 (Pearson) with at least one other descriptor. the Variable Selection Using Random Forest (VSURF) package has been used to select the best pool of descriptors.
</descriptors_selection>
<descriptors_generation chapter="4.5"  help="" name="Algorithm and descriptor generation">
NA
</descriptors_generation>
<descriptors_generation_software chapter="4.6"  help="" name="Software name and version for descriptor generation">
Dragon 7.0 extension for KNIME
</descriptors_generation_software>
<descriptors_chemicals_ratio chapter="4.7"  help="" name="Chemicals/Descriptors ratio">
315/17= 19
</descriptors_chemicals_ratio>
</QSAR_Algorithm>

<QSAR_Applicability_domain chapter="5"  help="" name="Defining the applicability domain - OECD Principle 3">
<app_domain_description chapter="5.1"  help="" name="Description of the applicability domain of the model">
The Applicability Domain (AD) is assessed using the original algorithm implemented within VEGA. An overall AD index is calculated, based on a number of parameters, which relate to the results obtained on similar chemicals within the training and test sets and is defined in this way for this QSAR model´s predictions:
If 1 ≥ AD index &amp;gt; 0.85, the predicted substance is regarded in the Applicability Domain of the model
If 0.85 ≥ AD index &amp;gt; 0.7, the predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model
If AD index ≤ 0.7, the predicted substance is regarded out of the Applicability Domain of the model
Indices are calculated on the first k = 2 most similar molecules, each having Sk similarity value with the target molecule.

Similarity index (IdxSimilarity) is calculated as:

[img src="/data/algaeec50irfmn/fig_sim_regr.png"]

where Diam is the difference in similarity values between the most similar molecule and the k-th molecule.

Accuracy index (IdxAccuracy) is calculated as:

[img src="/data/algaeec50irfmn/fig_acc_regr.png"]

where expc is the experimental value of the c-th molecule in the training set and predc is the c-th molecule predicted value by the model.

Concordance index (IdxConcordance) is calculated as:

[img src="/data/algaeec50irfmn/fig_conc_regr.png"]

where expc is the experimental value of the c-th molecule in the training set and predtarget is the predicted value for the input target molecule.

Max Error index (IdxMaxError) is calculated as:

[img src="/data/algaeec50irfmn/fig_maxerr_regr.png"]

where expc is the experimental value of the c-th molecule in the training set and predtarget is the predicted value for the input target molecule, evaluated over the k molecules.

ACF contribution (IdxACF) index is calculated as

[img src="/data/algaeec50irfmn/fig_acf.png"]

where: rare is calculated on the number of fragments found in the molecule and found in the training set in less than 3 occurences as following: if the number is 0, rare is set to 1.0; if the number is 1, rare is set to 0.6; otherwise rare is set to 0.4

missing is calculated on the number of fragments found in the molecule and never found in the training set as following: if the number is 0, missing is set to 1.0; if the number is 1, missing is set to 0.6; otherwise missing is set to 0.4

Descriptors Range (IdxDescRange) index is calculated as 1.0 if all molecular descriptors used in the prediction fall within the range of descriptors used in the whole training set, 0.0 otherwise.

AD final index is calculated as following:

[img src="/data/algaeec50irfmn/fig_ad.png"]

The initialADI index is the used together with the other sub-indices to calculate the final ADI, on the basis of the assessment class in which each sub-index falls:

IdxAccuracy  ≥	IdxConcordance ≥		IdxMaxError ≥	InitialADI ≥	ADI
1.5				1.5					1.5				0.85			1.0
0.8				0.8					0.8				0.7			0.85
All other cases													0.7
</app_domain_description>
<app_domain_method chapter="5.2"  help="" name="Method used to assess the applicability domain">
The Applicability Domain and the chemical similarity is measured with the algorithm developed for VEGA. Full details are in the VEGA website (www.vegahub.eu), including the open access paper describing it [1]. The VEGA AD also evaluates the correctness of the prediction on similar compounds (accuracy), the consistency between the predicted value for the target compound and the experimental values of the similar compounds, the range of the descriptors, and the presence of unusual fragments, using atom centered fragments.
Similar molecules with known experimental value:
This index takes into account how similar are the first two most similar compounds found. Values near 1 mean that the predicted compound is well represented in the dataset used to build the model, otherwise the prediction could be an extrapolation. Defined intervals are:

If 1 ≥ index &amp;gt; 0.85, strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found.

If 0.85 ≥ index &amp;gt; 0.7, only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found.

If index ≤ 0.7, no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found.

Accuracy (average error) of prediction for similar molecules:
This index takes into account the classification accuracy in prediction for the two most similar compounds found. Values near 1 mean that the predicted compounds fall in an area of the model's space where the model gives reliable predictions (no misclassifications), otherwise the lower is the value, the worse the model behaves. Defined intervals are:
If index &amp;lt; 0.8, accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good
If 1.5 &amp;gt; index ≥ 0.8, accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal
If index ≥ 1.5, accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate

Concordance for similar molecules: 
This index takes into account the difference between the predicted value and the experimental values of the two most similar compounds. Values near 0 mean that the prediction made disagrees with the values found in the model's space, thus the prediction could be unreliable. Defined intervals are:
If index &amp;lt; 0.8, molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value
If 1.5 &amp;gt; index ≥ 0.8, similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value
If index ≥ 1.5, similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value

Maximum error of prediction among similar molecules:
This index takes into account the maximum error in prediction among the two most similar compounds. Values near 0 means that the predicted compounds fall in an area of the model's space where the model gives reliable predictions without any outlier value. Defined intervals are:
If index &amp;lt; 0.8, the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability
If 1.5 &amp;gt; index ≥ 0.8, the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability
If index ≥ 1.5, the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability

Atom Centered Fragments similarity check: This index takes into account the presence of one or more fragments that aren't found in the training set, or that are rare fragments. First order atom centered fragments from all molecules in the training set are calculated, then compared with the first order atom centered fragments from the predicted compound; then the index is calculated as following: a first index RARE takes into account rare fragments (those who occur less than three times in the training set), having value of 1 if no such fragments are found, 0.85 if up to 2 fragments are found, 0.7 if more than 2 fragments are found; a second index NOTFOUND takes into account not found fragments, having value of 1 if no such fragments are found, 0.6 if a fragments is found, 0.4 if more than 1 fragment is found. Then, the final index is given as the product RARE * NOTFOUND. Defined intervals are:
If index = 1, all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set
If 1 &amp;gt; index ≥ 0.7, some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments
If index &amp;lt; 0.7, a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments

Model descriptors range check:
This index checks if the descriptors calculated for the predicted compound are inside the range of descriptors of the training and test set. The index has value 1 if all descriptors are inside the range, 0 if at least one descriptor is out of the range. Defined intervals are:
Index = TRUE, descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set
Index = FALSE, descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set
</app_domain_method>
<app_domain_software chapter="5.3"  help="" name="Software name and version for applicability domain assessment">
VEGA (www.vegahub.eu)
</app_domain_software>
<applicability_limits chapter="5.4"  help="" name="Limits of applicability">
The model is not applicable to inorganic chemicals and substances containing unusual elements (i.e., different from C, O, N, S, P, Cl, Br, F, I). Salts can be predicted only if converted to the neutralized form.
</applicability_limits>
</QSAR_Applicability_domain>

<QSAR_Robustness chapter="6"  help="" name="Internal validation - OECD Principle 4">
<training_set_availability chapter="6.1"  help="" name="Availability of the training set">
Yes
</training_set_availability>
<training_set_data chapter="6.2"  help="" name="Available information for the training set">
CAS RN: Yes
Chemical Name: Yes
Smiles: Yes
Formula: No
INChI: No
MOL file: Yes
NanoMaterial: No
</training_set_data>
<training_set_descriptors chapter="6.3"  help="" name="Data for each descriptor variable for the training set">
All
</training_set_descriptors>
<dependent_var_availability chapter="6.4"  help="" name="Data for the dependent variable for the training set">
All
</dependent_var_availability>
<other_info chapter="6.5"  help="" name="Other information about the training set">
The dataset was split in training (252 substances) and test (63 substances)
</other_info>
<preprocessing chapter="6.6"  help="" name="Pre-processing of data before modelling">
SMILES creation and neutralization
Firstly, we generated the SMILES structures from the chemical name and CAS RN for each substance using ChemCell (2019) and Marvin View (Marvin 17.28.0, 2012017, ChemAxon, 2019). We manually checked the correspondence and correctness among the obtained structures, chemical name and CAS RN among several websites and public database like ChemIDplus Advanced ( NIH, 2019), PubChem (NCBI, 2019), ChemSpider (Royal Society of Chemistry, 2019), DSSTox. Then, we added several structures, which have not automatically generated.
We normalized the SMILES with istMolBase 1.0.3. (in-house software), then we neutralized them using KNIME 3.5. Since pH is acritical issue in the experimental assays on algae, we considered ionized normalized SMILES and we calculated the major microspecies at pH 7.5 and 8.1 using JChem for Excel. We removed the compounds for which the SMILES changed depending on pH (in range 7.5-8.1).
Cleaning of the structure
We cleaned the datasets excluding the following compounds:
metal complexes
inorganics 
mixtures of structural isomers
ambiguous structures
non-ionic surfactant mixtures
complex disconnected structures (e.g. polymers) 
chemicals whose correspondence name-CAS was not found
UVCB
salts; only the acid form was kept.
Values cleaning
We selected continuous experimental values excluding those reported as a range, greater/less than a certain threshold, or approximate values. We converted each experimental value from mg/l to mmol/l, on the basis of the molecular weight calculated from the chemical structure. We also removed the compounds for which the experimental toxicity values were higher than the experimental water solubility values. For this purpose, we retrieved the experimental water solubility values mainly from a large database of more than 4,000 chemicals that we pruned in the LIFE project ANTARES and from GuideChem and Sigma-Aldrich websites in the case we did not find the water solubilities elsewhere.
According to the OECD guideline [3], two growth media can be used: one at pH 7.5 and another at pH 8.1. The two growth media can give different results, depending on the pH, especially for ionizing substances [3]. We had no information on what medium was used to perform the assays; therefore, we calculated the main microspecies at pH 7.5 and 8.1 for all the SMILES using JChem [4] and eliminated compounds with SMILES that changed depending on pH.
Dealing with multiple values
To deal with multiple continuous data we referred to the procedures described in ECHA guidance R.10 (2008) for ecotoxicological continuous endpoints. In case the experimental conditions and the reliability of the studies were the same, we considered the ratio between the maximum and the minimum values; if it was higher than one log unit we eliminated the data. Then, we calculated the median, the arithmetic and geometric mean in mmol/l to check if there were differences among them. We found a very good correlation between the values of each combination (arithmetic vs geometric mean, arithmetic mean vs median, geometric mean vs median) and finally the geometric mean was preferred (ECHA guidance R.10, 2008). To normalize the data we performed two types of transformation, the logarithm of the geometric mean and the Box-cox transformation. Since the box-cox transformation gave better results in terms of normalization of the data, it was finally used to normalize the data. We excluded data falling outside the range (mean of the box-cox transformed values) ± 3*(standard deviation). 
</preprocessing>
<goodness_of_fit chapter="6.7"  help="" name="Statistics for goodness-of-fit">
Training RMSE 0.67; R2 = 0.89; n = 252
</goodness_of_fit>
<loo chapter="6.8"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by leave-one-out cross-validation">
</loo>
<lmo chapter="6.9"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by leave-many-out cross-validation">
</lmo>
<yscrambling chapter="6.10"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by Y-scrambling">
</yscrambling>
<bootstrap chapter="6.11"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by bootstrap">
</bootstrap>
<other_statistics chapter="6.12"  help="" name="Robustness - Statistics obtained by other methods">
</other_statistics>
</QSAR_Robustness>

<QSAR_Predictivity chapter="7"  help="" name="External validation - OECD Principle 4">
<validation_set_availability chapter="7.1"  help="" name="Availability of the external validation set">
 Yes
</validation_set_availability>
<validation_set_data chapter="7.2"  help="" name="Available information for the external validation set">
CAS RN: No
Chemical Name: No
Smiles: Yes
Formula: No
INChI: No
MOL file: No
NanoMaterial: No
</validation_set_data>
<validation_set_descriptors chapter="7.3"  help="" name="Data for each descriptor variable for the external validation set">
</validation_set_descriptors>
<validation_dependent_var_availability chapter="7.4"  help="" name="Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set">
</validation_dependent_var_availability>
<validation_other_info chapter="7.5"  help="" name="Other information about the external validation set">
</validation_other_info>
<experimental_design chapter="7.6"  help="" name="Experimental design of test set">
</experimental_design>
<validation_predictivity chapter="7.7"  help="" name="Predictivity - Statistics obtained by external validation">
Test RMSE 1.35; R2 = 0.51; n = 63
Test set in AD: n 17, RMSE 0.53, R2 0.83
Test set Could be out of AD: n 17, RMSE 1.28, R2 0.64
Test set out of AD: n 29, RMSE 1.69, R2 0.34
</validation_predictivity>
<validation_assessment chapter="7.8"  help="" name="Predictivity - Assessment of the external validation set">
</validation_assessment>
<validation_comments chapter="7.9"  help="" name="Comments on the external validation of the model">
</validation_comments>
</QSAR_Predictivity>

<QSAR_Interpretation chapter="8"  help="" name="Providing a mechanistic interpretation - OECD Principle 5">
<mechanistic_basis chapter="8.1"  help="" name="Mechanistic basis of the model">
</mechanistic_basis>
<mechanistic_basis_comments chapter="8.2"  help="" name="A priori or a posteriori mechanistic interpretation">
</mechanistic_basis_comments>
<mechanistic_basis_info chapter="8.3"  help="" name="Other information about the mechanistic interpretation">
</mechanistic_basis_info>
</QSAR_Interpretation>

<QSAR_Miscelaneous chapter="9"  help="" name="Miscellaneous information">
<comments chapter="9.1"  help="" name="Comments">
</comments>
<bibliography chapter="9.2"  help="" name="Bibliography">
[1] Floris M, Manganaro A, Nicolotti O, Medda R, Mangiatordi GF, Benfenati E. A generalizable definition of chemical similarity for read-across. J Cheminform. 2014 Oct 18;6(1):39. doi: 10.1186/s13321-014-0039-1. PMID: 25383097; PMCID: PMC4212147
[2] Toma, C.; Cappelli, C. I.; Manganaro, A.; Lombardo, A.; Arning, J.; Benfenati, E. New Models to Predict the Acute and Chronic Toxicities of Representative Species of the Main Trophic Levels of Aquatic Environments. Molecules 2021, 26 (22), 6983. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26226983.
[3] OECD TG 201 (1984, 2006, 2011): Freshwater Alga and Cyanobacteria, Growth Inhibition Test
[4] J.Chem for Office J. ChemAxon. Available online: https://chemaxon.com/products/jchem-for-office (accessed on 5 October 2021).
</bibliography>
<attachments chapter="9.3"  help="" name="Supporting information">
Training set(s)Test set(s)Supporting information:
All available dataset are present in the model inside the VEGA software.
</attachments>
</QSAR_Miscelaneous>


</QMRF_chapters>
</QMRF>