<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Fish Acute (LC50) Toxicity classification (SarPy-IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>FISH_IRFMN</Key>
        <Summary>QSAR classification model for fish acute (LC50) toxicity</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.2</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_fish_irfmn.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>True</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Toxic-1 (less than 1 mg/l)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>2</Value>
                <Label>Toxic-2 (between 1 and 10 mg/l)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>3</Value>
                <Label>Toxic-3 (between 10 and 100 mg/l)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>4</Value>
                <Label>NON-Toxic (more than 100 mg/l)</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
        
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative evaluation (four toxicity classes) of fish toxicty. It has been developed using Sarpy software, by Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri and Politecnico di Milano. </Description>
        <Model>The model has been built as three sets of rules, extracted with Sarpy software, related to different toxicity classes. Each of the three set contains a list of relevant fragment (expressed in SMARTS notation) related to the first three toxicity classes, defined on the basis of the classification for toxicity to fish provided by Directive 92/32/EEC of the EU for dangerous substances:
            If one or more rules are verified for the given compound, the model will assign the compound to the most toxic class available among the verified rules. If no rules apply to the given compound, the prediction will be class 4.
            The extraction of the rules has been performed on a training set consisting of 567 compounds, where experimental data, originally expressed as acute toxicity database to fathead minnow (Pimephales promels), has been classified on the basis of the reported scheme. The experimental data have been retrieved from: C.L. Russom, S.P. Bradbury, D.E. Hammermeister, S.J. Drummond “Predicting modes of toxic action from chemical structure: acute toxicity in the fathead minnow (Pimephales promelas)” Environmental Toxicology Chemistry 16, 1997, pp. 948-967.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.5 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index >= 0.65</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.65</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
        <Structural_Alerts>
            Following, the list of the alerts, as SMARTS strings, related to class 1 toxicity:
            C(OCCCC)c1cccc(c1)
            c1cc(c(O)c(c1)C(C)C)
            Oc1ccc(cc1C)Cl
            O=Cc1cccc(Oc2ccc(cc2))c1
            Nc1ccc(cc1)CCCCCCCC
            O=[N+]([O-])c1c(cc(c(c1)[N+](=O)[O-])Cl)Cl
            NCCCCCCCCCCCC
            O(CC)P(=S)(OCC)SCS
            CC[Sn](CC)(CC)CC
            c1cc(ccc1CCl)
            O=CC=CC(=O)
            N#CCC#N
            [c]([Cl,Br,F])[c]([Cl,Br,F])[c]([Cl,Br,F])
            CCC(=O)OC[a]

            Following, the list of the alerts, as SMARTS strings, related to class 2 toxicity:
            Oc1ccc(cc1)Cl
            C(C)CCCCCCCCC
            c1ccc(Oc2ccccc2)cc1
            C(=O)Oc1ccccc1
            C(OCC=C)CC
            c1c(cccc1CC)CC
            O(CC)P(=S)(O)
            C=CC=C
            C(=O)OCCCC
            O=[N+]([O-])c1cc(cc(c1)C)
            c1cc(c(cc1C))C
            SCC
            O(c1ccccc1)CCCC
            c1cccc2ccccc12
            c1cc(ccc1O)Br
            c1ccccc1c2ccccc2
            O=Cc1c(F)cccc1
            I
            O=C(OC)CC
            [*;D1]#C[C;!D4][!C;D1]
            *[C;D2][C;D2][C;D2][C;D2][C;D2][C;D2]*
            [s;R]
            [$([c]([Cl,Br,F])[c]([Cl,Br,F])),$([c]([Cl,Br,F])[c][c]([Cl,Br,F]))]

            Following, the list of the alerts, as SMARTS strings, related to class 1 toxicity:
            C(OC)c1ccc(cc1)
            NCCCCCC
            c1cc(c(cc1)C)C
            Fc1ccccc1
            O=C(OCCC)C
            c1ccc(cc1)Br
            O=[N+]([O-])c1cc(N)ccc1
            c1ccc(cc1)CCCC
            C=CCCC
            c1ccc(cc1)Cl
            Oc1ccc(cc1)C
            c1cc(ccc1N(C)C)
            c1cc(N)ccc1O
            CCCCCCCC
            C(C(Cl))Cl
            O=P(OCC)(OCC)OCC
            N(CCC)(CCC)C
            o1c(ccc1)
            C#CCC(O)
            C(CCCl)C
            OCC#CC
            O=[C;D2][C;D2]
            C=C
            c1ccccc1
        </Structural_Alerts>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>567.0</n>
        <Specificity>0.741</Specificity>
        <Sensitivity>0.928</Sensitivity>
        <Accuracy>0.873</Accuracy>
        <Not_Predicted>0.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>


</xml>