<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Developmental/Reproductive Toxicity library (PG)</Name>
        <Key>DEVTOX_PG</Key>
        <Summary>Virtual compound library for Developmental/Reproductive (developed by Procter And Gamble)</Summary>
        <Version>1.1.0</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_devtox_pg.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Toxicant</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Toxicant</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not Classifiable</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>2</Value>
                <Label>Reproductive and developmental toxicant</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>3</Value>
                <Label>Reproductive toxicant, developmental NON-toxicant</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>4</Value>
                <Label>Reproductive toxicant (no data on developmental toxicity)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>5</Value>
                <Label>Developmental toxicant, reproductive NON-toxicant</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>6</Value>
                <Label>Reproductive and developmental NON-toxicant</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>7</Value>
                <Label>Reproductive NON-toxicant (no data on developmental toxicity)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>8</Value>
                <Label>Developmental toxicant (no data on reproductive toxicity)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>9</Value>
                <Label>Developmental NON-toxicant (no data on reproductive toxicity)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>10</Value>
                <Label>No data on reproductive and developmental toxicity</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction of developmental and reproductive toxicity, based on a virtual binary of possible toxicant compounds. It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/</Description>
        <Model>The model implements a virtual library of toxicant compounds as described in the study from Procter &amp;Gamble: Shengde Wu, Joan Fisher, Jorge M. Naciff, Michael C, Laufersweiler, Cathy Lester, George Daston, and Karen Blackburn “A Framework for Identifying Chemicals with Structural Features Associated with Potential to Act as Developmental or Reproductive Toxicants” Chem. Res. Toxicol., 2013, 26 (12), pp 1840–1861.
            In the work from Procter &amp; Gamble, 25 categories of possible toxicant have been identified, and for each category an extended list of virtual compounds have been generated. The model implements these categories, and tries to find an exact match between the given compound and any of the virtual compounds in the library. If a match is found, a prediction of “Toxicant” is given, otherwise a “NON-Toxicant” prediction is provided.
            The original dataset used in the cited work, consisting of 641 compounds, has been implemented as the training set.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.75</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.75</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.5 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 > index >= 0.65</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.65</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
        <Categories_ToxicantCompounds>
            Following, the list of the 25 categories of toxicant compounds implemented:
            Category 1: Inorganics and derivatives: metals, metallic derivatives, organophosphorus and
            organosiloxane compounds
            Category 2: Estrogen receptor (ER) and androgen receptor (AR) binding compounds
            Category 3: Retinoic acid receptor (RAR), aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AhR) binders and prostaglandin
            receptor agonists
            Category 4: Nicotinic acetyl choline receptor (nAChR) binders and acetyl cholineesterase (AChE)
            inhibitors
            Category 5: Ion channel opener/inhibitor, beta-adrenergic inhibitors, ACE/ARA inhibitors and Shh
            signaling interference/Cholesterol synthesis inhibition
            Category 6: Opioid receptor binders and tubulin receptor interactors
            Category 7: Nucleotide and nucleobase derivatives
            Category 8: Aromatic compounds with alkyl, multi-halogen and nitro groups
            Category 9: Aromatic compounds contain alkyl chain with alcohol, aldehyde, acid functional groups;
            poly-Cl aryloxy derived acids and esters
            Category 10: Aromatic compounds with sulfonamide and urea moieties, phenytoins
            Category 11: Aromatic compounds (non-fused ring system) with aliphatic amine moieties
            Category 12: Aromatic diamine, their diazo moieties, and aromatic triazene derivatives
            Category 13: Imidazole, nitro imidazoles derivatives, nitro-furfurylideneamino and triazole derivatives
            Category 14: Aromatic ring fused cyclic-, heterocyclic derivatives
            Category 15: Miscellaneous aromatic chemicals and antibiotics
            Category 16: Non-aromatic cyclic hydrocarbon ring, heterocyclic ring contain only oxgen atom and
            multi Cl single/fused cyclic hydrocarbons
            Category 17: Heterocyclic, cyclic compounds contain nitrogen, oxygen/sulfur atoms
            Category 18: Miscellaneous cyclic chemicals
            Category 19: Alkyl carbamodi-thioic acids, alkyl sulfonates and perfluorinated compounds (PFCs)
            Category 20: Miscellaneous non-cyclic chemicals
            Category 21: Vinyl amides, aldehydes, esters and alkyl amides (&lt;C4), N-substituted amides, ureas,
            carbonates, guanidine and carbamates
            Category 22: Alpha-substituted carboxylic acids, esters and di-acid derived esters
            Category 23: Small- (C1-C4) halo-, multihalo-alkanes, alkyl ether/alkenes and halogenated
            acetonitriles as well as N, or S related mustards
            Category 24: Di/multi-OH, NH2, substituted amine, SH (=S), OR, OAc substituted (at each terminal
            carbon) C1 to C5 hydrocarbon chain or repeating C2 units as well as metal chelators
            Category 25: C1 to C4 non-branched/&lt;C9 beta-alkyl (&lt;C5) substituted alcohols and &lt;C4 alkyl, vinyl
            nitriles
        </Categories_ToxicantCompounds>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats></Stats>

</xml>