<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Thyroid Receptor Beta effect (NRMEA)</Name>
        <Key>TRBETA_NRMEA</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for Thyroid Receptor Beta effect ((NRMEA)).</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_thyroid_trbeta.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not predicted</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>Inactive</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Agonist</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>2</Value>
                <Label>Antagonist</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>3</Value>
                <Label>A-Anta</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction of the effect of compound on Thyroid receptor beta.</Description>
        <Dataset>Model are built based on two in vitro assays: i) reporter gene assay and ii) cytotoxicity. Chemical data were collected from two open free libraries, including ToxCast/Tox21 (https://www.epa.gov/chemical-research/toxcast-dashboard) and ChEMBL (https://www.ebi.ac.uk/chembl/).
            All of the chemical data were prepared by removing all false SMILES strings, and deleting all duplicate compounds. Then, the data set was split randomly into training set and test set in the ratio of 4:1 (KNIME Analytics Platform, https://www.knime.com/). The training set was used to provide feature fragments and local physicochemical properties present across the completely active set. The test set was used in the external validation.</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>Hierarchy fragment features model is a hierarchical tree on three levels: fragments on first and second levels define if a compound is active on receptor, third fragments define the type of activity of the compounds on the receptor.
            Firstly, we took advantage of primary fragments to select compounds have the possibility of being active. Secondly, compounds were screened by secondary fragments according to their different types of primary fragments. Each compound contains primary and secondary fragments simultaneously, would be predicted as active compounds. Next, the types of disrupting activities of identified active compounds would be distinguished based on their tertiary fragments. This hierarchy fragments allow the exploration of a wide range of structurally diverse active compounds which could bind to receptors, and build up an array of rules focusing on Agonist/A-Anta/Antagonist disruption. Structural fragments are calculating using substructure frequency analysis and substructure percentage analysis, and PubChem fingerprint database was used to generate primary fragments to describe active disruptors as much as possible. According to the structural features, chemicals were divided into several subtypes based on their primary fragments. Then, specific secondary fragments were generated by using SARpy software (https://www.vegahub.eu/portfolio-item/sarpy/). Active disruptors, containing primary and related secondary fragments, were used to extracted disrupting tertiary fragments. Disruptors were clustered according to their primary and secondary fragments, then, tertiary fragments were extracted independently by using SARpy software.
            Chemicals/insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors ratio: 5462 chemicals/ 26 structural alerts

            The model uses:
            Padel-descriptor (for primary fragment)
            https://www.softpedia.com/get/Science-CAD/PaDELDescriptor.shtml.
            SARpy software (for secondary and tertiary fragment) https://www.vegahub.eu/portfolio-item/sarpy</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>The model has been developed by
        [1]Alberto Manganaro, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy alberto.manganaro@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
        [2]Tan Haoyue, State Key Laboratory of Pollution Control and Resources Reuse, School of the Environment, Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu 210023, China. Tan Haoyue 417695798@qq.com
        [3]Wei Shi, State Key Laboratory of Pollution Control and Resources Reuse, School of the Environment, Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu 210023, China. Wei Shi njushiwei@nju.edu.cn
        on 24 September 2019
        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>Data are from Human. The model provides a qualitative prediction of the effect of compound on Thyroid receptor beta.</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <Specificity_Train_Active-Inactive>0.998</Specificity_Train_Active-Inactive>
        <Sensitivity_Train_Active-Inactive>0.83</Sensitivity_Train_Active-Inactive>
        <Accuracy_Train_Active-Inactive>0.995</Accuracy_Train_Active-Inactive>
        <Accuracy_Train_Agonist-Antagonist>0.98</Accuracy_Train_Agonist-Antagonist>
        <Specificity_Test_Active-Inactive>0.997</Specificity_Test_Active-Inactive>
        <Sensitivity_Test_Active-Inactive>0.71</Sensitivity_Test_Active-Inactive>
        <Accuracy_Test_Active-Inactive>0.99</Accuracy_Test_Active-Inactive>
        <Accuracy_Test_Agonist-Antagonist>1</Accuracy_Test_Agonist-Antagonist>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>