<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>KOA model (OPERA)</Name>
        <Key>KOA_OPERA</Key>
        <Summary>KNN model for KOA (octanol/air coefficient)</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_koa_opera.dat</TS>
        <Guide>/insilico/model/guide/VEGA_model_guide_KOA_OPERA_1_0_0.pdf</Guide>
        <Units>log units</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative estimation of the Octanol-air partition coefficient (KOA). The partition coefficient is a ratio of concentrations of un-ionized compound between the two phases. It is based on k nearest neighbor (k-NN) model and it is an implementation of the same model present in OPERA.</Description>
        <Model>The model is based on 270 chemicals collected from “An automated curation procedure for addressing chemical errors and inconsistencies in public datasets used in QSAR modeling. 2016. Kamel Mansouri, Chris M. Grulke, Ann M. Richard, Richard S. Judson and Antony J. Williams. SAR and QSAR in Environ. Res; Vol. 27 , Iss. 11,2016.”
            The model implemented is a distance weighted k-nearest neighbors (kNN), with k equal to 5. This is a refinement of the classical k-NN classification algorithm where the contribution of each of the k neighbors is weighted according to their distance to the query point, giving greater weight to closer neighbors. The used distance is the Euclidean distance calculated from a set of descriptors selected with a genetic algorithm.
            The descriptors used are calculated with Padel (http://www.yapcwsoft.com/dd/padeldescriptor/) libraries.
            Below, the list of descriptors used to derive the model:
            nHBDon	Number of hydrogen bond donors (using CDK HBondDonorCountDescriptor algorithm)
            MLFER_L	Solute gas-hexadecane partition coefficient

            More information can be obtained from:
            OPERA: A free and open source QSAR tool for physicochemical properties and environmental
            fate predictions. Kamel Mansouri, Chris Grulke, Richard Judson, Antony Williams, Journal of
            Cheminformatics (2018)</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.75</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.75 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt; 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 > index > 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt; 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.75</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.75 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <R2_Train_Mansouri>0.95</R2_Train_Mansouri>
        <RMSE_Train_Mansouri>0.65</RMSE_Train_Mansouri>
        <R2_Test_Mansouri>0.96</R2_Test_Mansouri>
        <RMSE_Test_Mansouri>0.68</RMSE_Test_Mansouri>
        <n_Vega>270</n_Vega>
        <R2_Vega>0.96</R2_Vega>
        <RMSE_Vega>0.62</RMSE_Vega>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>