<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>In vitro Micronucleus activity (IRFMN-VERMEER)</Name>
        <Key>MNVITRO_VERMEER</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for In vitro Micronucleus activity (IRFMN/VERMEER).</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_micronucleus_vitro.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>True</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not predicted</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>Inactive</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Active</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The in vitro micronucleus activity model provides a qualitative prediction of genotoxicity as induction of micronucleus in mammalian cells in vitro.
            Micronuclei are small cytoplasmic bodies originated from chromosome fragments or whole chromosomes that were unable to migrate to the poles during anaphase in cell division. The assay is typically performed with human or rodent cell lines or primary cell cultures and it can discriminate between clastogens and aneugens.
            Micronuclei induction is a genotoxicity endpoint because it highlights the ability of an agent to cause DNA damage as an alteration in the structure of genetic material in cells.
            The model is based on a set of rules extracted from a set of compounds by SARpy software without any ‘a priori’ knowledge.</Description>
        <Model>The model has been developed by Diego Baderna, Emilio Benfenati and Alberto Manganaro from the Laboratory of Environmental Chemistry and Toxicology, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCCS on December 2019.</Model>
        <Dataset>The model is based on genotoxic effect in terms of induction of micronuclei in vitro, as binary classification: non-genotoxic (0) and genotoxic (1).
            The dataset include 380 compounds with experimental data collected from peer-reviewed literature, SCCS and EFSA opinions, ECVAM guidelines and review, and eChemPortal inventory. The collection, slightly imbalanced toward genotoxicants (about 60% of the set), includes chemicals from all the commercial and production sectors for which genotoxicity testing is required including drugs, plant protection products, industrial reagents, and PCPs ingredients. We carefully revised the sources to ensure their quality and reliability and, to our knowledge, most of the selected data can be classified with a Klimisch score of 1 due to the facts that the studies were done with test procedure in accordance with validated standard methods. Data were selected according to their adherence to the OECD 487 guideline considering only data related to experiments conducted with human peripheral blood lymphocytes, CHO, V79, CHL/IU, L5178Y, TK6, HT29, Caco-2, HepaRG, HepG2, A549 and primary Syrian Hamster Embryo cells as cell lines listed in the guideline. Regarding the use of post-mitochondrial liver fraction (S9), we included data from experiments with S9 and positive data from studies without S9 metabolic activation.
            A published KNIME workflow for chemical data retrieval and quality checking was used to automatically retrieve SMILES of the chemicals. For each chemical, the structural data are retrieved automatically from four sound web-based chemo-informatic sources (National Cancer Institute (NCI) Chemical Identifier Resolver (CIR), the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) CompTox Chemistry Dashboard, PubChem and ChemIDPlus) using chemical name and CAS as input. Structural data that are consistent among all the web databases are further cleaned to remove inorganic and organometallic compounds, isomeric mixtures, polymers and data related to mixtures of chemicals. In the end, the neutralized SMILES are converted into a standardized QSAR-ready format using the OpenBabel KNIME implementation to generate Canonical SMILES. The curated structures were then split into training and test sets according to their structural similarity. Briefly, fingerprints of the structures in the dataset were calculated using the RDKit Fingerprint node and Morgan fingerprints as implemented in KNIME (version 4.0.2). The structural similarity was estimated with the Distance Matrix KNIME node using the Tanimoto function. A k-Medoids clustering algorithm was applied on the distance matrix followed by a partitioning node to split the dataset in training and test sets, with an analogue chemical distribution, in an 80:20 ratio.
            The training set includes 293 organic chemicals while the validation set includes 87 organic chemicals from all the commercial and production sectors for which genotoxicity testing is required including drugs, plant protection products, industrial reagents, and PCPs ingredients.
            Available information for dataset include CAS registry number, SMILES and Activity (binary adimensional classification).</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>Prediction of the genotoxic/non-genotoxic activity of chemical is based on selected structural alerts, applying the rule ‘‘IF contains SA THEN apply activity label’’ and considering their Likehood Ratio (LR) values. The algorithm generates substructures of arbitrary complexity, and the fragment candidates to become structural alerts (SAs) are automatically selected based on their prediction performance on a training set. Fragmentation is done directly on the SMILES notation of structures. Positive (genotoxic) and negative (non-genotoxic) rules were found. If at least one rule is matching with the target compound, a prediction is given according to the type of rule (positive or negative); if no rules match with the given compound, no prediction is given.
            The descriptors used in the model include 82 genotoxic and 56 non-genotoxic adimensional Structural Alerts (SAs) selected from a larger list of SAs automatically extracted with SARpy. Only structural alerts with LR higher than 2 were considered for the development of the model to obtain a more accurate model minimizing the occurrence of wrong predictions. The ChemicalsDescriptors ratio is 293/138 = 2.12 considering only the training set, used to extract the SAs.
            The structural alerts were extracted using the software SARpy (SAR in python, version 1.0), a freely available software in the VEGA HUB platform (www.vegahub.eu). SARpy automatically extracts sets of rules by generating and selecting substructures based on their prediction performance on a training set used as input. The selection is made with a 3-steps process: 1) the fragmentation of chemicals to extract all the substructures within a user-customizable size range; 2) a validation step to derive the predictive power of each fragment through the analysis of the correlation between the occurrence of each molecular substructure and the experimental activity of the compounds containing the fragment; 3) a selection step in which the most predictive fragments are listed in the form of rules ‘‘IF contains SA THEN apply activity label". SARpy was applied to extract SAs for both positive (genotoxicant) and negative (non-genotoxicant) activity. Various runs with different settings for alert precision were done to obtain fragments with high accuracy or with high coverage.</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>It has been described here: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.121638 “Baderna, D., Gadaleta, D., Lostaglio, E., Selvestrel, G., Raitano, G., Golbamaki, A., Lombardo, A., Benfenati, E., 2020. New in silico models to predict in vitro micronucleus induction as marker of genotoxicity. Journal of Hazardous Materials 385. “
        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>In vitro mammalian cell lines according to the OECD guideline no 487. It is included in the category TOX 7.6.1. Genetic toxicity in vitro.
        Micronuclei are small cytoplasmic bodies originated from chromosome fragments or whole chromosomes that were unable to migrate to the poles during anaphase in cell division. The assay is typically performed with human or rodent cell lines or primary cell cultures and it can discriminate between clastogens and aneugens. Micronuclei induction is a genotoxicity endpoint because it highlights the ability of an agent to cause DNA damage as an alteration in the structure of genetic material in cells.</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>293.0</n_Train>
        <Specificity_Train>0.73</Specificity_Train>
        <Sensitivity_Train>0.97</Sensitivity_Train>
        <Accuracy_Train>0.88</Accuracy_Train>
        <n_Test>87.0</n_Test>
        <Specificity_Test>0.63</Specificity_Test>
        <Sensitivity_Test>0.94</Sensitivity_Test>
        <Accuracy_Test>0.83</Accuracy_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>12</Not_Predicted_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>50</Not_Predicted_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>