<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>LogP model (MLogP)</Name>
        <Key>LOGP_MLOGP</Key>
        <Summary>LogP model based on MLogP descriptor.</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.0</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_logp_mlogp.dat</TS>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction of water/octanol partition coefficient (LogP). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vega-qsar.eu/</Description>
        <Model>The model is based on the the Moriguchi LogP (MLogP) and consists of a regression equation based on 13 structural parameters as described in:
            I.Moriguchi, S.Hirono, Q.Liu, I.Nakagome, and Y.Matsushita, Chem.Pharm.Bull. 1992, 40, 127-130;
            I.Moriguchi, S.Hirono, I.Nakagome, H.Hirano, Chem.Pharm.Bull. 1994, 42, 976-978.
            For the purpose of applicability domain assessment, the training set of the Meylan LogP model (9,961 compounds) has been considered, setting all molecules as belonging to the test set.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.75</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.75</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 => index > 0.75</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.75</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>9961.0</n>
        <R2>0.717</R2>
        <RMSE>0.963</RMSE>
        <Not_Predicted>0.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>