<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Carcinogenicity oral classification model (IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>CARC_SFO_CLASS</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for carcinogenicity (oral route).</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_carc_sfoclassification.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Carcinogen</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Carcinogen</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction of oral carcinogenic potency (expert assessment based on presence of carcinogenic effects in rodents). It is based on a classification and regression trees (CART) method and it is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vegahub.eu/.</Description>
        <Model>The model has been developed by Alberto Manganaro, Kode srl, info@kode-solutions.net, in 2017.</Model>
        <Dataset>It has been developed using data from the Risk Assessment Information System (RAIS) Toxicity values database (https://rais.ornl.gov). Data cover different pollutants categories including organic and inorganic compounds such as dioxins, polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs, pesticides and metals frequently found in contaminated sites.1110 values were retrieved for oral slope factor (OSF, mg/kg-day)-1).
            Canonical SMILES were retrieved for each chemical from two sources (JChem for Office and ChemID plus) then chemicals showing incongruences between the various sources were rejected. Most of the QSAR models cannot handle inorganic compounds, metals and metal complexes, organic salts and data related to mixtures and these compounds have been also rejected. Ionized structures were neutralized and counterions eliminated. The datasets were further checked for the presence of duplicates.
            For the training/test splitting, constitutional and ring descriptors blocks have been used, together with the experimental class value, as input for a principal components analysis (PCA). The first principal component (PC) has been used to rank the compounds, then a venetian blind approach has been used to split training and test set compounds with an 80-20% ratio.
            The training set contains 593 compounds. The test set counts 149 compounds.</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>Classification and regression trees (CART). CART implementation in R (rpart package) Recursive partitioning for classification, regression and survival trees. An implementation of most of the functionality of the 1984 book by Breiman, Friedman, Olshen and Stone. The descriptors have been generated with VEGA software using CDK libraries.
            The model uses these descriptors:
            [1]nS number of Sulfur atoms
            [2]nCIC number of rings (cyclomatic number)
            [3]ATSC6s Centred Broto-Moreau autocorrelation of lag 6 weighted by I-state
            [4]P_VSA_logp_6 P_VSA-like on LogP, bin 6
            [5]SpMax_EA(dm) leading eigenvalue from edge adjacency mat. weighted by dipole moment [6]B02[C-N] Presence/absence of C - N at topological distance 2
            [7]B09[C-F] Presence/absence of C - F at topological distance 9

            An in-house tool developed in the R statistical platform has been used to select the best descriptors set and size to be employed for the final model. The approach was based on a forward selection technique: starting from the descriptor most correlated with the experimental data, at each iteration the descriptor leading to the best model (among all the available descriptors) was added, until the size of 25 descriptors. Models have been built with a Linear Discriminant Analysis (LDA) modelling and applied with a bootstrap cross-validation approach (n = 100 iterations). The fitness function has been calculated for each model as a linear combination of the mean values of the accuracy, sensitivity and specificity obtained from the models built in each bootstrap iteration. This function has been used to select the best descriptor to be added to proceed to the next iteration.</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>It has been described here:
        Benfenati E, Roncaglioni A, Lombardo A, Manganaro A. Integrating QSAR, Read-Across, and Screening Tools: The VEGAHUB Platform as an Example. Advances in Computational Toxicology: Springer; 2019. p. 365-81.
        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>Section TOX 7.7. Carcinogenicity. Different species (rodents). </Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>593.0</n_Train>
        <Specificity_Train>0.79</Specificity_Train>
        <Sensitivity_Train>0.82</Sensitivity_Train>
        <Accuracy_Train>0.81</Accuracy_Train>
        <n_Test>149.0</n_Test>
        <Specificity_Test>0.76</Specificity_Test>
        <Sensitivity_Test>0.76</Sensitivity_Test>
        <Accuracy_Test>0.76</Accuracy_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>