<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>NOAEL (IRFMN-CORAL)</Name>
        <Key>NOAEL_CORAL</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for NOAEL.</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_noael_coral.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>-log(mg/kg)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model is based on experiments with rat and other rodents. It is a one variable model based on 2D descriptor.</Description>
        <Model>The model has been developed by:
            Giovanna J. Lavado, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCSS, Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy (giovanna.lavado@marionegri.it) https://www.marionegri.it/
            Andrey Toropov, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCSS, Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy (andrey.toropov@marionegri.it) https://www.marionegri.it/
            Alla Toropova, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCSS, Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy (alla.toropova@marionegri.it) https://www.marionegri.it/

            Date of model development and/or publication: April, 2015</Model>
        <Dataset>The model is based on experiments with rat and other rodents.
            Endpoint units: NOAEL = mmol/kg/day
            Dependent variable:-logNOAEL
            Experimental protocol: Repeated dose 90 day oral toxicity study in rodents, Test Guideline No. 408
            Endpoint data quality and variability: All doubtful or inorganic compounds, salts, and mixtures were eliminated, because the relationships between molecular structure and the NOAEL are very complex. We considered only data referring to 90 days of oral administration in rats and rejected reproductive toxicity studies. It is to be noted that the exchange of the 90 day study by shorter testing is an attractive alternative. Taking into account this circumstance, values for 28 days of treatment were considered but, in order to have consistent data, they were divided by a factor of 3, as specified by the scientific committee on consumer safety (SCCS) in order to approximate the 90 day NOAEL. After the above selection, about four hundreds of various substances with small molecules (e.g., 2 3 atoms) and vice versa with extremely large molecules (e.g., 100 or more atoms), molecules with specific groups, such as [N+], [NH4+], [nH], etc., and substances with molecules containing many various cycles / heterocycles were remained. Under such circumstances, the following limitations were used in the selection of compounds for the work set: (i) too large and, vice versa, too small molecules were removed (practically, molecules which can be represented by SMILES with length less than 70 and larger than 10 symbols, were selected); (ii) molecules which have only one cycles or have no cycles at all were selected; and (iii) molecules with special groups (indicated by square brackets) were removed from the work set. Thus, the dataset of 140 compounds has been selected. All values were converted to decimal logarithms (logNOAEL).
            Pre-processing of data before modelling: The SMILES were taken from OECD toolbox v3.2
            Availability of the training set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the training set: All
            Availability of the external validation set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set: All
            Other information about the training set: The initial dataset was divided into three sets (training, calibration, and validation) using a random distribution.
            Other information about the external validation set: NA</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>Type of model: One variable model based on 2D descriptor
            Explicit algorithm: The Monte Carlo method
            LogNOAEL = 2.1680835 + 0.0 737528 * DCW( 1,30) , where T*=1 and N*=30.
            Algorithm and descriptor generation: The Monte Carlo Method
            Software name and version for descriptor generation:
            CORAL 2016, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCCS, 20156 Milano, Italy
            http://www.insilico.eu/coral/
            The model uses optimal 2D descriptors.
            insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors in the model: NA
            Descriptor selection: 2D optimal descriptor

            DCW(T,N) = CW(NOSP) + CW(HALO) + CW(BOND) + ∑ CW(EC0k ) + ∑CW(SAk)
            Algorithm and descriptor generation: The Monte Carlo Method
            Software name and version for descriptor generation:
            CORAL 2016, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCCS, 20156 Milano, Italy
            http://www.insilico.eu/coral/</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 1.2 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>It has been described here:
        CORAL: model for no observed adverse effect level (NOAEL). Molecular Diversity, 19(3), (2015) 563-575. https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11030-015-9587-1

        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G. VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>The endpoint is the repeated dose toxicity oral
        Species: Rat and other rodents.
        Endpoint: TOX 7.5. 1. Repeated dose toxicity oral
        Comment on endpoint: NA
        Endpoint units: NOAEL = mmol/kg/day</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>97</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.53</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.61</RMSE_Train>
        <F_Train>107</F_Train>
        <n_Calibration>16</n_Calibration>
        <R2_Calibration>0.73</R2_Calibration>
        <RMSE_Calibration>0.49</RMSE_Calibration>
        <n_Test>27</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.60</R2_Test>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>