<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>MOA fish toxicity classification (EPA T.E.S.T.)</Name>
        <Key>MOA_EPA</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for MOA fish toxicity</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.2</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_moa_epa.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>AChE Inhibition</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Anticoagulation</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>2</Value>
                <Label>nACHr Antagonism</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>3</Value>
                <Label>Narcosis</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>4</Value>
                <Label>Neurotoxicity</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>5</Value>
                <Label>Reactivity</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>6</Value>
                <Label>Uncoupler</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>N/A</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative estimation for the Mode of action of Chemicals in Fathead Minnow (Pimephales promelas) 96 h. It is based on a series of Linear Discriminant Analysis (LDA) models and it is an implementation of T.E.S.T mode of action profiler.</Description>
        <Model>The model is based on 958 chemicals collected from T.E.S.T. training set. The models implemented are described in: Martin, T. M.; Grulke, C. M.; Young, D. M.; Russom, C. L.; Wang, N. Y.; Jackson, C. R.; Barron, M. G. Prediction of Aquatic Toxicity Mode of Action Using Linear Discriminant and Random Forest Models. J. Chem. Inf. Model. 2013, 53, 2229-2239.
            Six models have been implemented from the paper:
            AChE Inhibition
            Anticoagulation
            ACHr Antagonism
            Narcosis
            Neurotoxicity
            Reactivity
            The highest score obtained by running the six models is will be the estimated Mode of Action of the selected chemical. If all the models have a LDA score under 0.5 the prediction is not provided.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>757.0</n_Train>
        <Balanced_accuracy_Train>0.888</Balanced_accuracy_Train>
        <MCC_Train>0.875</MCC_Train>
        <n_Test>200.0</n_Test>
        <Balanced_accuracy_Test>0.796</Balanced_accuracy_Test>
        <MCC_Test>0.792</MCC_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>51</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>22</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>