<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Adipose tissue - blood model (INERIS)</Name>
        <Key>TISSUEBLOOD_INERIS</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for adipose tissue:blood partition coefficient on rat</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/tissuebloodineris/ts_tissueblood_ineris.dat</TS>
        <QMRF>/data/tissuebloodineris/qmrf_adipose_blood.xml</QMRF>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>Log units</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The Adipose tissue: blood model (INERIS) is based on 63 blood partition coefficient (KAB). Model is based on Random Forest (RF) approach. The endpoint is the adipose tissue: blood partition coefficient (KAB) is a key-endpoint to predict the bioaccumulation and the pharmacokinetics in humans and animals, since other organ: blood affinities can be estimated as a function of this parameter.</Description>
        <Dataset>The Random Forest model is based on 63 experimental data (Log (KAB)), selected according to the OECD TG 417 guideline.
            Availability of the training set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the training set: NA
            Availability of the external validation set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set: NA
            Other information about the training set: Training set: n = 63
            Other information about the external validation set: Training set: n = 38</Dataset>
        <Descriptors>The model is based on Random Forest (RF) approach. In particular Machine Learning Algorithm for Regression has been used. The number of trees selected for the RF were finely tuned by identifying the onset of the plateau of the curve describing the Q2LOO as a function of the number of trees.
            The "randomForest" v. 4.6.14 in R v. 3.4.3 have been used. The "randomForest" package provides an R interface to the Fortran programs by Breiman and Cutlert (http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/users/breiman/).
            The model uses PaDEL-Descriptors v. 2.21 PaDEL computes the 2D descriptors. "VSURF" v. 1.0.4 package was used.</Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index > 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index > 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt; 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>The model has been developed by Alberto Manganaro Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy alberto.manganaro@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/  in 2019.
        It has been described here:
        [1] Cappelli CI, Manganelli, Toma C, Emilio Benfenati E, Mombelli E Prediction of the Partition Coefficient between Adipose Tissue and Blood for Environmental Chemicals: from Single QSAR Models to an Integrated Approach Mol. Inf. 2020, 39, 2000072, DOI: 10.1002/minf.202000072
        [2] Benfenati E, Roncaglioni A, Lombardo A, Manganaro A. Integrating QSAR, Read-Across, and Screening Tools: The VEGAHUB Platform as an Example. Advances in Computational Toxicology; Springer; 2019. p. 365-81.
        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>The endpoint is TOX Adipose tissue: blood partition coefficient (KAB). It represents a key-endpoint to predict the bioaccumulation and the pharmacokinetics in humans and animals, since other organ: blood affinities can be estimated as a function of this parameter. The species is RAT. </Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <Q2_LOO>0.73</Q2_LOO>
        <Q2_ext>0.87</Q2_ext>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>