<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Daphnia Magna Acute (EC50) Toxicity model (IRFMN-Combase)</Name>
        <Key>DAPHNIA_COMBASE</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for acute toxicity (EC50) in daphnia magna, specific for biocides</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.0</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_daphnia_combase.dat</TS>
        <QMRF>/insilico/model/daphnia/combase/data/QMRF_Daphnia_combase.pdf</QMRF>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>log(mmol/l)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction of acute toxicity in Daphnia Magna (EC50), given in log(mmol/L) and converted in mg/L. It has been developed inside the EU LIFE COMBASE project (LIFE15 ENV/ES/416). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/. </Description>
        <Model>133 biocides with experimental data on EC50 48h Daphnia magna (expressed as Log mmol/L). The dataset has been acquired from several public sources:
            - the OECD QSAR toolbox v. 4.2 (www.qsartoolbox.org),
            - the Pesticide Properties Database (PPDB) database (https://sitem.herts.ac.uk/aeru/ppdb/),
            - the Office of Pesticide Programs (OPP) Pesticides Ecotoxicity Database
            (http://www.ipmcenters.org/ecotox/)),
            - the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) (http://www.efsa.europa.eu/) database and
            The quality of the experimental data has been evaluated taking into account all the criteria required by the official guideline OECD 202.
            CORAL (http://www.insilico.eu/coral) was used to develop a regression QSAR model from SMILESbased optimal descriptors. A CORAL mathematical model describes the relationship between an
            endpoint (dependent variable) and relevant SMILES attributes (independent variable), as explained in:
            Toropov, A.A., Toropova, A.P., Roncaglioni, A., Benfenati, E. "Prediction of biochemical endpoints by the CORAL software: Prejudices, Paradoxes, and Results" (2018) Methods in Molecular Biology, 1800, pp. 573-583.
            The final model formula obtained with CORAL is:
            Endpoint = 0.5569253 (± 0.0797226) + 0.1098193 (± 0.0022561) * DCW(1,35)
            where DCW is represented by the following formula, see section 1.4 for the list of CORAL fragments used in the model and their correlation weights:
        </Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>99.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.724</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>1.237</RMSE_Train>
        <n_Test>34.0</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.597</R2_Test>
        <RMSE_Test>1.082</RMSE_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>