<xml>

    <Version>
        <Name>Mutagenicity (Ames test) model (ISS)</Name>
        <Key>MUTA_ISS</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for Mutagenicity (Ames test) based on Benigni-Bossa (Istituto Superiore di Sanità) rule set</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.3</Version>
    </Version>

    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_muta_bb.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>True</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Mutagenic</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Mutagenic</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not classifiable</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction of mutagenicity on Salmonella typhimurium (Ames test). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vega-qsar.eu/</Description>
        <Model>The model has been built as a set of rules, taken from the work of Benigni and Bossa (ISS) as implemented in the software ToxTree version 2.6 (http://toxtree.sourceforge.net): Benigni, R., Bossa, C. “Mechanisms of chemical carcinogenicity and mutagenicity: a review with implications for predictive toxicology”, Chem. Revs. 111 (2011), 2507-2536; Benigni, R., Bossa C., Tcheremenskaia O. “In vitro cell transformation assays for an integrated, alternative assessment of carcinogenicity: a databased analysis”, Mutagenesis (2013), 28(1):107-16.
            The model implement all the rules related to mutagenicity and does not implement the full decision tree used by ToxTree. If at least one mutagenicity rule is matching with the given compound, a “mutagen” prediction is given; otherwise, a “non-mutagen” prediction is given. The training set for the model has been extracted from ToxTree, and consists of 670 compounds.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 > index >= 0.65</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.65</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
        <Structural_Alerts>Following, the list of the rules for mutagenicity extracted from ToxTree:
            SA1 Acyl halides
            SA2 Alkyl (C&lt;5) or benzyl ester of sulphonic or phosphonic acid
            SA3 N-methylol derivatives
            SA4 Monohaloalkene
            SA5 S or N mustard
            SA6 Propiolactones and propiosultones
            SA7 Epoxides and aziridines
            SA8 Aliphatic halogens
            SA9 Alkyl nitrite
            SA10 alfa, beta unsaturated carbonyls
            SA11 Simple aldehyde
            SA12 Quinones
            SA13 Hydrazine
            SA14 Aliphatic azo and azoxy
            SA15 Isocyanate and isothiocyanate groups
            SA16 Alkyl carbamate and thiocarbamate
            SA18 Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons
            SA19 Heterocyclic Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons
            SA21 Alkyl and aryl N-nitroso groups
            SA22 Azide and triazene groups
            SA23 Aliphatic N-nitro
            SA24 alfa,beta unsaturated alkoxy
            SA25 Aromatic nitroso group
            SA26 Aromatic ring N-oxide
            SA27 Nitro aromatic
            SA28 Primary aromatic amine, hydroxyl amine and its derived esters (with restrictions)
            SA28bis Aromatic mono- and dialkylamine
            4SA28ter Aromatic N-acyl amine
            SA29 Aromatic diazo
            SA30 Coumarins and Furocoumarins
            SA37 Pyrrolizidine Alkaloids
            SA38 Alkenylbenzenes
            SA39 Steroidal estrogens
            SA57 DNA Intercalating Agents with a basic side chain
            SA58 Haloalkene cysteine S-conjugates
            SA59 Xanthones, Thioxanthones, Acridones
            SA60 Flavonoids
            SA61 Alkyl hydroperoxides
            SA62 N-acyloxy-N -alkoxybenzamides
            SA63 N-aryl-N-acetoxyacetamides
            SA64 Hydroxamic acid derivatives
            SA65 Halofuranones
            SA66 Anthrones
            SA67 Triphenylimidazole and related
            SA68 9,10 - dihydrophenanthrenes
            SA69 Fluorinated quinolines
        </Structural_Alerts>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>670.0</n>
        <Specificity>0.696</Specificity>
        <Sensitivity>0.888</Sensitivity>
        <Accuracy>0.791</Accuracy>
        <Not_Predicted>0.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>

</xml>