<xml>

    <Version>
        <Name>Sludge (EC50) Toxicity model (ProtoQSAR-Combase)</Name>
        <Key>SLUDGE_COMBASEEC50</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for toxicity (EC50) in sludge, specific for biocides</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.0</Version>
    </Version>

    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_sludge_combaseEC50.dat</TS>
        <LocalQMRF>/data/QMRF_sludge_life.pdf</LocalQMRF>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>log(mg/L)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction for toxic compounds for Activated Sludge EC50 (3 hours), given in log (mg/L) and converted in mg/L. It has been developed inside the EU LIFE COMBASE project (LIFE15 ENV/ES/416). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http:// www.vega-qsar.eu/. </Description>
        <Model>A biocide-like chemical space was developed comparing 6512 chemical structures from the Physprop database and 257 chemical structures of biocides from COMBASE database. Five molecular descriptors were selected as filters. These filters were applied to the experimental data found within the different databases from the QSAR Toolbox V 4.2 (https://qsartoolbox.org/).
            Firstly, 94 biocide-like compounds were found by application of the biocide-chemical space, and were used to develop the qualitative model settling the cut-off to discriminate between a toxic and a non-toxic compound in 100 mg/L. The quantitative model was developed using the compounds considered toxic in the dataset. A Multiple Linear Regression model using a Forward Stepwise approach for variable selection was performed using 35 chemical compounds. The descriptors used in the model are the following:
            MinHBint: Minimum E-State descriptors of strength for potential Hydrogen Bonds of path length 2 ATSC7v: Centered Broto-Moreau autocorrelation - lag 7 / weighted by van der Waals volumes VE3_DzZ: Logarithmic coefficient sum of the last eigenvector from Barysz matrix / weighted by
            atomic number
            AATSC4e: Average centered Broto-Moreau autocorrelation - lag 4 / weighted by Sanderson
            electronegativities
            BCUTp-1l: nhigh lowest polarizability weighted BCUTS
            The descriptors were calculated, in the original model, by means of the open-source PaDEL libraries. Part of their code has been ported in the VEGA libraries to reproduce the descriptors.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt; 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>35.0</n>
        <R2>0.706</R2>
        <RMSE>0.163</RMSE>
        <Not_Predicted>0.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>

</xml>