<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Aromatase activity model (IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>AROM_IRMFN</Key>
        <Summary>Qualitative model for aromatase activity</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_aromatase_irfmn.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>Inactive</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Active agonist</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>2</Value>
                <Label>Active antagonist</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not predicted</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>        
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model is based on Aromatase Breast cancer cell line (MCF-7 aro) Cell-based assay and measures the inhibition of the conversion of testosterone to estradiol catalyzed by aromatase of 3254 compounds. The control used for this assay is Letrozole (IC50 =9.44 ± 1.4 nM (n =27)). It is a Random Forest model.</Description>
        <Model>The model has been developed by:
            [1] Cosimo Toma Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy cosimo.toma@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
            [2] Alberto Manganaro Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri - IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy alberto.manganaro@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/</Model>
        <Dataset>The dataset is composed by 3254 compounds, with 281 active agonists, 170 active antagonists, and 2803 inactive.
            For modeling purposes, the Endpoint (AC50) is transformed in molar log10.
            The procedure of curation of data involved the analysis of purity (only samples labeled with purity A are kept) and the outcome of the test (all the assays labeled as inconclusive are discarded). All the samples with additional flags are discarded as well. For each compound, several assays could be performed. Only compounds with the same outcome are kept. AC50 of the compounds was the mean of each sample. If the span between AC50 was too large, the compounds are excluded.
            SMILES have been retrieved with an in-house data curation workflow. This is a semi-automated procedure that addresses automatic chemical data retrieval (i.e., SMILES) from different, orthogonal web-based databases, by using two different identifiers, chemical name and CAS registration number. Records were scored based on the coherence of information retrieved from different web sources (DSStox, Cactvs, Pubchem and Chemid).
            Data curation procedure performed to top scored records. The procedure includes removal of inorganic and organometallic compounds and mixtures, neutralization of salts, removal of duplicates, checking of tautomeric forms. SMILES have been normalized with VEGA notation. One of the compounds (Fortretamine) is incorrectly recognized as aromatic so it has been manually corrected. From the original dataset here are the compounds maintained/rejected, with the relative reason:
            Maintain (with duplicates): 3401
            Rejected (mixtures): 3
            Rejected (inorganic or unusual elements): 10
            Checked manually: 119
            Rejected (missing/ambiguous): 67
            The experimental values are then added to the 3401 compounds. Duplicates are merged in order to keep a unique value for each structure. The experimental value for the duplicates has been maintained only if the Assay outcome was coherent among all members (rejected 6 compounds). The final dataset has 3254 compounds, with 281 active agonists, 170 active antagonists, and 2803 inactive.
            Pre-processing of data before modelling: Descriptors are centered and autoscaled before modeling
            Availability of the training set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the training set: All
            Availability of the external validation set: Yes.
            Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set: All.
            Other information about the training set: Dataset n = 292</Dataset>
        <Descriptors>The type of model used is Random Forest, in particular Weighted Random Forest. Data sampling for each tree was done with replacement, and the default number of randomly chosen descriptors at each split was the square root, these attributes being different for each tree. A weighted importance has given to the errors related to conazoles.
            DRAGON 7.0 has been used to generate SMILES and to calculate the descriptors (Dragon 7.0
            Calculation of several sets of molecular descriptors from molecular geometries (topological, geometrical, WHIM, 3D-MoRSE, molecular profiles, etc.)
            Kode srl. Via Nino Pisano, 14 56122 Pisa (PI) - Italy, info@kode-solutions.net www.kode-solutions.net https://chm.kode-solutions.net/products_dragon.php)
            The model uses 18 descriptors:
            [1] SpMax2_Bh(m)
            [2] SpMax2_Bh(p)
            [3] SpMaxA_AEA(dm)
            [4] piPC08
            [5] piPC09
            [6] MLOGP
            [7] P_VSA_MR_6
            [8] X5sol
            [9] ATSC4p
            [10] Eig03_EA(bo)
            [11] SsssN
            [12] SM6_B(m)
            [13] nRNR2
            [14] ATS5s
            [15] SssNH
            [16] H-049
            [17] F02[C-N]
            [18] SM15_EA(ed)

            From 3850 2D descriptors has been applied: Variance filter, Correlation filter, VSURF. Feature selection has then applied only on the training set. After discarding all the descriptors that correlated over 0.95 (Pearson) with at least another, a Feature Selection has been performed with R package VSURF [3]. VSURF is a three-steps variable selection based the RF algorithm. The first step is based on evaluating variable importance of descriptors selecting a certain threshold. The second step finds important descriptors highly closely related to the response variable (interpretation step) and the third step (prediction step) evaluates the number of descriptors that are sufficient to have good performance. In order to treat unbalancing of dataset, the parameter strata (vector for stratified sampling) is added to assure that all the classes of the dataset are passed in every tree grown.</Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>It has been described here:
        [1] Benfenati E, Roncaglioni A, Lombardo A, Manganaro A. Integrating QSAR, Read-Across, and Screening Tools: The VEGAHUB Platform as an Example. Advances in Computational Toxicology; Springer; 2019. p. 365-81.
        [2] Chemistry Development Kit (CDK) http://sourceforge.net/apps/mediawiki/cdk/index.php?title=Main_Page
        [3] Malot, C., VSURF: An R Package for Variable Selection Using Random Forests. The R Journal 2015, 7, 19-33.
        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>The endpoint is IN VITRO Endocrine disruptor mammalian sceeening - in vitro Tox21_Aromatase_Inhibition (activity test) (AC50). The species analysed is human.
        This assay is based on Aromatase Breast cancer cell line (MCF-7 aro) Cell-based assay and measures the inhibition of the conversion of testosterone to estradiol catalyzed by aromatase. The control used for this assay is Letrozole (IC50 =9.44 ± 1.4 nM (n =27)).</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>2602.0</n_Train>
        <Specificity_Train>1.0</Specificity_Train>
        <Sensitivity_Train>0.583</Sensitivity_Train>
        <Accuracy_Train>0.942</Accuracy_Train>
        <n_Test>652.0</n_Test>
        <Specificity_Test>0.998</Specificity_Test>
        <Sensitivity_Test>0.516</Sensitivity_Test>
        <Accuracy_Test>0.931</Accuracy_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>