<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Fish Acute (LC50) Toxicity model (NIC)</Name>
        <Key>FISH_NIC</Key>
        <Summary>QSAR quantitative model for fish acute toxicity (by NIC)</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_fish_nic.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>log(1/(mmol/L))</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction of acute toxicity in fish (LC50), given in log(1/(mmol/L)). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vegahub.eu.</Description>
        <Model>The model has been built as a Counter Propagation Artificial Neural Network (CP ANN) by the National Institute of Chemistry Slovenia (NIC). The model has been built on a set of 946 compounds, retrieved from the paper:

            LM. Su, X. Liu, Y. Wang, J.J. Li, X.H. Wang, L.X. Sheng, Y.H. Zhao, “The discrimination of excess toxicity from baseline effect: Effect of bioconcentration”, Science of the Total Environment 484 (2014) 137–145

            The descriptors used by the CPANN are the following:
            - nCIR: number of circuits
            - nTB: number of Triple Bonds
            - nP: number of P atoms
            - nCL: number of Cl atoms
            - nR10: number of 10-membered rings
            - TI1: first Mohar index from Laplace matrix
            - S2K: 2-path Kier alpha-modified shape index
            - T(N..P): sum of topological distances between N..P
            - T(P..Cl): sum of topological distances between P..Cl
            - T(Cl..Cl): sum of topological distances between Cl..Cl
            - piPC09: molecular multiple path count of order 9
            - PCR: ratio of multiple path count over path count
            - Xindex: Balaban X index
            - MATS1e: Moran autocorrelation - lag 1/weighted by Sanderson electronegativity
            - GATS7m: Geary autocorrelation - lag 7/weighted by mass
            - EEig14x: eigenvalue n. 14 from edge adjacency matrix weighted by edge degree
            - EEig14d: eigenvalue n. 14 from edge adjacency matrix weighted by dipole moment
            - ESpm01d: spectral moment of order 1 rom edge adjacency matrix weighted by dipole moment
            - GGI4: topological charge index of order 4
            - Seigv: spectral moment of order 1 from Brysz matrix weighted by van der Waals volume

            The descriptors were calculated, in the original model, by means of Dragon software and are now entirely calculated by an in-house software module in which they are implemented as described in: R. Todeschini and V. Consonni, Molecular Descriptors for Chemoinformatics, Wiley-VCH, 2009.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>The endpoint is the short-term toxicity to fish according to ECOTOX 6.1.1 (LC50 96h, acute (mortality)).  The specie is Fish (Oryzias latipes). </Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>564.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.89</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.42</RMSE_Train>
        <n_Test>382.0</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.54</R2_Test>
        <RMSE_Test>0.90</RMSE_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>
</xml>