<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Carcinogenicity model (CAESAR)</Name>
        <Key>CARC_CAESAR</Key>
        <Summary>QSAR classification model for Carcinogenicity (from CAESAR project)</Summary>
        <Version>2.1.9</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_carc_caesar.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Carcinogen</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Carcinogen</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not predicted</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction of carcinogenic potency according to specific requirements of Chemical regulation. It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/.
        TThe model extends the original CAESAR model, freely available at: http://www.caesar-project.eu/software/ </Description>
        <Model>The model has been built as a Counter Propagation Artificial Neural Network (CP ANN). The neural network output consists of two values labeled as Positive and Non-Positive, both in the range [0,1] and with sum equal to 1; they represent how much the neuron in which the predicted compound falls belongs to the class of carcinogenic or non-carcinogenic compounds. The higher between these two values leads to the prediction. Full reference and details of the used formulas can be found in:
        Fjodorova N., Vračko M., Novič M., Roncaglioni A. and Benfenati E. New public QSAR model for carcinogenicity. Chemistry Central Journal (2010), 4 (Suppl 1):S3 </Model>
        <Descriptors>The descriptors used are the following:
            - BEHm1: highest eigenvalue n. 1 of Burden matrix / weighted by atomic masses
            - Eig1p: Leading eigenvalue from polarizability weighted distance matrix
            - IC2: information content index (neighborhood symmetry of 2-order)
            - IDE: mean information content on the distance equality
            - MLOGP: Moriguchi octanol-water partition coeff. (logP)
            - Mp: mean atomic polarizability (scaled on Carbon atom)
            - MW: molecular weight
            - nHAcc: number of acceptor atoms for H-bonds (N O F)
            - nNR2Ph: number of tertiary amines (aromatic)
            - nP: number of Phosphorous atoms
            - O-057: phenol / enol / carboxyl OH
            - O-060: Al-O-Ar / Ar-O-Ar / R..O..R / R-O-C=X
            - S-107: R2S / RS-SR; Class: atom-centred fragments
            - SRW05: self-returning walk count of order 05
            - T(F..Cl): sum of topologica</Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Reliability</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>model class assignment is well defined</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = 0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>model class assignment is uncertain</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>NMN_concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted value agrees with experimental values of training set compounds laying in the same neuron</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>index = 0.75</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted value disagrees with experimental values of training set compounds laying in the same neuron</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index = 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance falls into a neuron that is populated by no compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 = index >= 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>645.0</n_Train>
        <Specificity_Train>0.859</Specificity_Train>
        <Sensitivity_Train>0.895</Sensitivity_Train>
        <Accuracy_Train>0.878</Accuracy_Train>
        <n_Test>161.0</n_Test>
        <Specificity_Test>0.597</Specificity_Test>
        <Sensitivity_Test>0.719</Sensitivity_Test>
        <Accuracy_Test>0.665</Accuracy_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>