<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Algae Acute (EC50) Toxicity model (ProtoQSAR-Combase)</Name>
        <Key>ALGAE_COMBASEEC50</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for acute toxicity (EC50) in algae, specific for biocides</Summary>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_algae_combaseEC50.dat</TS>
        <QMRF>/data/QMRF_Life_algae.pdf</QMRF>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>log(mg/L)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction for Pseudokirchneriella subcapitata EC50 (72 hours), given in log (mg/L) and converted in mg/L. It has been developed inside the EU LIFE COMBASE project (LIFE15 ENV/ES/416). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/. </Description>
        <Model>A biocide-like chemical space was developed comparing 6512 chemical structures from the Physprop database and 257 chemical structures of biocides from COMBASE database. Five molecular descriptors were selected as filters. These filters were applied to the Japanese Ministry of Environment dataset for acute aquatic toxicity in algae (650 compounds), and finally we obtained a data set of 361 biocide-like structures.</Model>
        <Descriptors>The quantitative model has been developed using a Support Vector Machine (SVM). The set was divided in training set (253) and validation set (108) and the descriptors in the model are the following:
            ATS5m: Broto-Moreau autocorrelation of a topological structure - lag 5 / weighted by atomic masses
            B01[O-S]: Presence/absence of O - S at topological distance 01
            B02[N-Cl]: Presence/absence of N - Cl at topological distance 02
            B02[N-O]: Presence/absence of N - O at topological distance 02
            B03[O-Cl]: Presence/absence of O - Cl at topological distance 03
            B05[C-S]: Presence/absence of C - S at topological distance 05
            B06[N-Cl]: Presence/absence of N - Cl at topological distance 06
            B07[N-O]: Presence/absence of N - O at topological distance 07
            B09[C-C]: Presence/absence of C - C at topological distance 09
            F01[C-O]: Frequency of C - O at topological distance 01 2D frequency fingerprints
            F05[O-O]: Frequency of O - O at topological distance 05
            MATS5m: Moran autocorrelation - lag 5 / weighted by atomic masses
            nR10: Number of 10-membered rings
            X3A: Average connectivity index chi-3
            X3sol: Solvation connectivity index chi-3
            The descriptors were calculated, in the original model, by means of Dragon software and are now entirely calculated by an in-house software module in which they are implemented as described in: R. Todeschini and V. Consonni, Molecular Descriptors for Chemoinformatics, Wiley-VCH, 2009.</Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt; 1.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>252.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.765</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.6</RMSE_Train>
        <n_Test>109.0</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.72</R2_Test>
        <RMSE_Test>0.639</RMSE_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>