<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Estrogen Receptor Relative Binding Affinity model (IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>RBA_IRFMN</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for Estrogen Receptor Relative Binding Affinity (IRFMN)</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.2</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_rba_irfmn.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>Inactive</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Active</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction for Relative Binding Affinity (RBA) for endocrine disruptor screening. It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: https://www.vegahub.eu/</Description>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>The model is a QSAR classification model based on a classification and regression tree (CART) algorithm, as described in:

        A. Roncaglioni, N. Piclin, M. Pintore, E. Benfenati, "Binary classification models for endocrine disrupter effects mediated through the estrogen receptor", SAR and QSAR in Environmental Research (2008), 19, 7-8

        The descriptors used by the model are the following:
        - X2v: Valence connectivity index chi-2
        - MATS6m: Moran autocorrelation – lag 6 / weighted by atomic masses
        - MATS8v: Moran autocorrelation – lag 8 / weighted by atomic van der Waals volumes
        - MATS5p: Moran autocorrelation – lag 5 / weighted by atomic polarizabilities
        - BEH2e: Highest eigenvalue no. 2 of Burden matrix/weighted by atomic Sanderson electronegativities
        - BEH1p: Highest eigenvalue no. 1 of Burden matrix/weighted by atomic polarizabilities
        - nArOH: Number of aromatic hydroxyls
        - MlogP: Moriguchi octanol-water partition coeff. (log P)

        The training set of the model, taken from the cited work, consists of 806 compounds.</Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>656.0</n_Train>
        <Specificity_Train>0.85</Specificity_Train>
        <Sensitivity_Train>0.87</Sensitivity_Train>
        <Accuracy_Train>0.86</Accuracy_Train>
        <n_Test>150.0</n_Test>
        <Specificity_Test>0.88</Specificity_Test>
        <Sensitivity_Test>0.78</Sensitivity_Test>
        <Accuracy_Test>0.84</Accuracy_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>