<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>BCF model (Meylan)</Name>
        <Key>BCF_MEYLAN</Key>
        <Summary>QSAR regression model for fish BCF (based on Meylan model)</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.3</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_bcf_meylan.dat</TS>
        <Units>log(L/kg)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction of bioconcentration factor (BCF) in fish, given in log(L/kg). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/ The model implements the Meylan model, as described in EPI Suite BCFBAF module:
            http://www.epa.gov/oppt/exposure/pubs/episuite.htm</Description>
        <Model>The model is based on the method proposed by Meylan et al (Meylan W.M., Howard P.H., Boethling R.S. et al. Improved Method for Estimating Bioconcentration / Bioaccumulation Factor from Octanol/Water Partition Coefficient. 1999, Environ. Toxicol. Chem. 18(4): 664-672) et implemented in the EPI Suite BCFBAF module (http://www.epa.gov/oppt/exposure/pubs/episuite.htm). The model provides a BCF prediction based on different regression equations or fixed values, selected on the basis of an initial classification between ionic and non-ionic compounds, and on the value of the predicted logP value.
            For the purpose of the model, ionic compounds include carboxylic acids, sulfonic acids and salts of sulfonic acids, and charged nitrogen compounds (nitrogen with a +5 valence such as quaternary ammonium compounds). All other compounds are classified as non-ionic. The logP prediction is provided by the VEGA logP model.
            The original dataset from EPI Suite has been taken, then processed and cleared from duplicates and compounds provided with structure that had problems. The final dataset has 662 compounds.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.75</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.75</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt; 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>LogP_reliability</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>reliability of logP value used by the model is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>index = 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>reliability of logP value used by the model is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index = 0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>reliability of logP value used by the model is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.75</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.75</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>516.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.798</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.547</RMSE_Train>
        <n_Test>146.0</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.791</R2_Test>
        <RMSE_Test>0.649</RMSE_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>


</xml>