<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Guppy LC50 model (KNN-IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>GUPPY_KNN</Key>
        <Summary>KNN model for acute toxicity on guppy</Summary>
        <Version>1.1.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_guppy_knn.dat</TS>
        <Units>log 1/LC50(mmol/L)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative evaluation for acute lethal toxicity in guppy (Poecilia reticulata). It has been developed using a k-NN modelling approach, by Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri.</Description>
        <Model>The model is based on 207 chemicals collected from Su et al., 2014. It is based on the similarity index developed inside the VEGA platform (Floris et al. "A generalizable definition of chemical similarity for read-across." Journal of cheminformatics 6.1 (2014): 39).
            The first 2 similar compounds in the training set according to the similarity index are used for the prediction. If the mean similarity value of these compound is lower than 0.85 prediction is not provided.
            Prediction is not provided when only one neighbor is found and it has a similarity value lower than 0.8.
            The prediction is calculated as the weighted average value of the experimental values of the compounds selected with the above mentioned procedure, with an enhance factor of 2.
            If the range of activity between the selected compounds is above 3fold (minimum activity is less than 1/3 than the maximum) the prediction is discarded.</Model>
        <Applicability_domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.75</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.75 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt; 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt; 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.5</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.5 &lt;= index &lt; 1.0</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.0</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.75</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.75 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>207.0</n>
        <R2>0.869</R2>
        <RMSE>0.472</RMSE>
        <Not_Predicted>1.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>