<xml>

    <Version>
        <Name>Mutagenicity (Ames test) model (KNN-Read-Across)</Name>
        <Key>MUTA_KNN</Key>
        <Summary>KNN (Read-Across) model for Mutagenicity (Ames test)</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>

    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_muta_knn.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Mutagenic</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Mutagenic</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-999</Value>
                <Label>Non Predicted</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model performs a read-across and provides a qualitative prediction of mutagenicity on Salmonella typhimurium (Ames test). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vega-qsar.eu/</Description>
        <Model>The model performs a read-across on a dataset of 5770 chemicals. This dataset has been made by Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri, merging experimental data from a benchmark dataset compiled by Hansen and colleagues (Hansen K, Mika S, Schroeter T, Sutter A, ter Laak A, Steger-Hartmann T, Heinrich N, Muller KR. “Benchmark data set for in silico prediction of Ames mutagenicity”, J Chem Inf Model, 2009, 49, 2077–2081) and from a collection of data made available by the Japan Health Ministry within their Ames (Q)SAR project.
            The read-across model has been built with the istKNN application (developed by Kode srl, http://chm.kode-solutions.net) and it is based on the similarity index developed inside the VEGA platform; the index takes into account several structural aspects of the compounds, such as their fingerprint, the number of atoms, of cycles, of heteroatoms, of halogen atoms, and of particular fragments (such as nitro groups). The index value ranges from 1 (maximum similarity) to 0.
            On the basis of this structural similarity index, the four compounds from the dataset resulting most similar to the chemical to be predicted are taken into account; compounds with a similarity value lower than 0.7 are discarded. If no compounds fall under these conditions, no prediction is provided. The estimated toxicity class is calculated as the most represented class among the chosen similar compounds, where the similarity value of each compound is also taken into account as a weight.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 >= index > 0.5 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.5</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.9</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.9 > index >= 0.65</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.65</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>5770.0</n>
        <Specificity>0.759</Specificity>
        <Sensitivity>0.832</Sensitivity>
        <Accuracy>0.8</Accuracy>
        <Not_Predicted>0.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>


</xml>