<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Carcinogenicity model (IRFMN-ISSCAN-CGX)</Name>
        <Key>CARC_ISSCAN-CGX</Key>
        <Summary>QSAR classification model for Carcinogenicity (IRFMN/ISSCAN-CGX) based on the ISSCAN-CGX dataset</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.0</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_carc_isscancgx.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>True</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Carcinogen</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Carcinogen</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Possible NON-Carcinogen</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction of carcinogenicity (expert assessment based on carcinogenic effects in different species). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vega-qsar.eu/</Description>
        <Model>The model has been built as a set of rules, extracted with Sarpy software from a dataset obtained from the union of the ISS carcinogenicity (ISSCAN) database from Istituto Superiore della Sanità, and of the Carcinogenicity Genotoxicity eXperience (CGX) dataset.
            The Sarpy software has been used with a cross-validated procedure, ending with the extraction of a set of 43 rules (structural alerts) related to carcinogenic activity. These rules are expressed SMARTS representing molecular fragments.
            If at least one rule is matching with the given compound, a “Carcinogen” prediction is given. Otherwise, a “Possible NON-Carcinogen” prediction is given.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index >= 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
        <Structural_Alerts>
            Following, the list of the 127 rules for carcinogenicity, expressed as SMARTS strings:
            SA 1: O=NNCC
            SA 2: c1occc1
            SA 3: O=CN(N)C
            SA 4: CCCN(CC)CC
            SA 5: C1CC(=CC)CCC1
            SA 6: Nc1ccc(cc1C)C
            SA 7: NCCCN
            SA 8: O=S(=O)(OC)
            SA 9: c1ccc2OCOc2c1
            SA 10: Nc1ncccc1
            SA 11: N(CCCl)CCCl
            SA 12: c1cn(cnc1)
            SA 13: C=C(C=C)C
            SA 14: O=NNC
            SA 15: O=P(OC)
            SA 16: O(c1ccc(cc1)CC=C)
            SA 17: c1ncn(c1)C
            SA 18: C(CCCC(CC)Cl)Cl
            SA 19: c1ncsc1
            SA 20: C=CCN
            SA 21: O=Cc1ccccc1O
            SA 22: O(c1ccc(cc1N))C
            SA 23: O1CC1C
            SA 24: SN(C)C
            SA 25: C(CCl)Cl
            SA 26: c1c(cc(cc1Cl)Cl)Cl
            SA 27: NNCC
            4SA 28: O=CN(N)
            SA 29: C(OC)C(C)C
            SA 30: c1ccc2cc(ccc2c1)
            SA 31: Nc1cccc(c1C)C
            SA 32: NNc1ccccc1
            SA 33: c1cc(ccc1C)Cl
            SA 34: N(CCO)CCO
            SA 35: Nc1ccc(cc1N)
            SA 36: c1ccc(cc1N)C
            SA 37: O(c1ccc(cc1)C)C
            SA 38: C(c1ccccc1)CO
            SA 39: C(=CCC)CC
            SA 40: N(Cc1ccccc1)C
            SA 41: Nc1ccc(cc1)C
            SA 42: Nc1ccccc1
            SA 43: n1cccc(c1)
        </Structural_Alerts>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>986.0</n>
        <Specificity>0.802</Specificity>
        <Sensitivity>0.587</Sensitivity>
        <Accuracy>0.642</Accuracy>
        <Not_Predicted>0.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>