<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Daphnia Magna Acute (EC50) Toxicity model (IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>DAPHNIA_EC50</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for acute toxicity (EC50) in daphnia magna</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.3</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_daphnia_ec50.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>log(mmol/l)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The Daphnia magna acute (EC50) Toxicity (IRFMN) model provides a quantitative prediction of acute toxicity in the freshwater crustacean Daphnia magna after 48h exposure to chemicals. The toxicity assay is described in the OECD guideline 202 “Daphnia sp. Acute Immobilization Test” (2004): young daphnids, aged less than 24 hours at the start of the test, are exposed to the test substance at a range of concentrations for 48 hours. Immobilisation is recorded at 24 and 48 hours and compared with control values and the results are analysed to calculate the EC50 (concentration estimated to immobilise 50% of the daphnids) at 48h.
            The model is a Tree Ensemble Random Forest made on 12 molecular descriptors associated to toxicity towards daphnids.</Description>
        <Model>The model has been developed by Cosimo Toma, Claudia I. Cappelli, Emilio Benfenati and Alberto Manganaro from the Laboratory of Environmental Chemistry and Toxicology, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCCS on April 2019.</Model>
        <Dataset>The model is a Tree Ensemble Random Forest made on 12 molecular descriptors associated to Daphnia sp. Toxicity.
            The dataset includes 445 compounds with experimental data retrieved the Japanese Ministry of Environment (http://www.env.go.jp/en/chemi/sesaku/aquatic_Mar_2016.pdf) and selected according to the OECD TG 202 requirements. The training set includes 312 organic chemicals while the validation set includes 133 organic chemicals. Available information for dataset includes chemical name, CAS registry number, SMILES and the toxicity value for 48h EC50.
            SMILES structures were generated from the chemical name and CAS RN for each substance using ChemCell and Marvin View. The correspondence and correctness among the obtained structures, chemical name and CAS RN were checked among several websites and public database (ChemIDplus Advanced, PubChem, ChemSpider, DSSTox, …). For dataset pruning, metal complexes, inorganics, mixtures of structural isomers, ambiguous structures, non-ionic surfactant mixtures, complex disconnected structures (e.g. polymers), chemicals whose correspondence name-CAS was not found, UVCB were excluded. Salts were converted into their acid form.
            Only continuous experimental values were maintained excluding data reported as a range, as greater/less than a certain threshold, or as approximate values. Finally, the molecular weight from each chemical structure were calculated to change the experimental toxicity value from mg/l to mmol/l. The experimental toxicity values were higher than the water solubility values, chemicals and the associated data were removed from the dataset. Data were randomly split in training and test set with the ratio of 80:20. An activity and descriptors sampling method was applied to obtain a uniform distribution of the endpoint values between the two subsets.</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>The acute toxicity of chemical towards daphnids is predicted by a Tree Ensemble Random Forest based on 12 molecular descriptors. Tree ensemble builds a series of regression trees with different rows and different variables (according to certain parameters) and then the results are aggregated as an ensemble of models. The parameters for the variables of each tree and the number of compounds are chosen evaluating the performance of several models (Hyperparameter tuning Research) using as metric R2 of a Bootstrap (100 iterations) cross-validation on training set. A genetic algorithm (R package gaselect) have been used to select the best pool of descriptors.
            Selected descriptors are: [1] S.106 R-SH, [2] Me mean atomic Sanderson electronegativity (scaled on Carbon atom), [3] MATS5e Moran autocorrelation of lag 5 weighted by Sanderson electronegativity, [4] MATS4p Moran autocorrelation of lag 4 weighted by polarizability, [5] GATS1m Geary autocorrelation of lag 1 weighted by mass, [6] EEig15bo eigenvalue n. 15 from edge adjacency mat. weighted by bond order, [7] EEig8dm eigenvalue n. 8 from edge adjacency mat. weighted by dipole moment, [8] B2.C..O. Presence/absence of C - O at topological distance 2, [9] B10.C..N. Presence/absence of C - N at topological distance 10, [10] F4.Cl..Cl. Frequency of Cl - Cl at topological distance 4, [11] F10.O..O. Frequency of O - O at topological distance 10  and [12] ALogP Ghose-Crippen octanol-water partition coeff. (logP). The ChemicalsDescriptors ratio is 312/12 = 26 considering only the training set.</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>The endpoint of the model is the acute toxicity towards the freshwater crustacean Daphnia magna according to the OECD guideline no 202. It is included in the category ECOTOX 6.1.3. Short-term toxicity to aquatic inverterbrates. Toxicity is expressed as 48h EC50 as concentration of the chemical estimated to immobilise 50% of the daphnids after exposure of 48h. A limit test at 100 mg/l of test substance (or up to its limit of solubility in the test medium) is done to demonstrate that the EC50 is greater than this concentration. If EC50 is higher than 100 mg/L, the substance can be classified as non-toxic.</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>312.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.68</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>062</RMSE_Train>
        <n_Train>312.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.7</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>061</RMSE_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>