<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Skin Permeation (LogKp) model (Ten Berge)</Name>
        <Key>SKINPERM_TENBERGE</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for skin permeation (LogKp), Ten Berge 3 formula.</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_skin_perm_tenberge.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>log(cm/h)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model is a Physiologically based kinetic/dynamic model that provides a prediction of the skin permeability coefficient value (Kp). Kp represents the rate of chemical penetrating across the skin. </Description>
        <Dataset>The model is based on a dataset of 271 compounds. Following the criteria reported in the OECD guideline 428, only data obtained in compliance with the following features have been kept:
            All the data are retrieved from “in vitro” experiments
            Data are collected from human skin experiments
            Studies concerned skin application of chemicals dissolved in water, aqueous solution, water gel, PBS and distilled water
            The buffer solution at a pH of 7.4
            The permeation coefficients were measured under comparable circumstances.
            The model is an application of the ten Berge equation to the entire dataset. For this reason, a splitting into training and test set is not provided.</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>It is a PBK/D model based on the following equation:
            log[𝐾𝑝𝑠𝑘−𝑤𝑎𝑡𝑒𝑟] =log[1/(1/𝑘𝑙𝑖𝑝+𝑘𝑝𝑜𝑙) +1/𝑘𝑎𝑞]
            Where:
            ▪𝐾𝑝𝑜𝑙 = 𝑏4/𝑀𝑊𝑏5
            ▪𝐾𝑎𝑞 = 𝑏6/𝑀𝑊𝑏7
            ▪Klip = 10[𝑏1+𝑏2∗10log(𝐾o/w) +𝑏3∗𝑀W]
            ▪Klip = permeation coefficient lipid medium
            ▪Kpol = permeation coefficient corneocytes [proteins]
            ▪Kaq = permeation coefficient epidermis [aqueous]
            ▪Ko/w= octanol/water partition coefficient
            ▪MW= Molecular weight
            ▪b1, b2, b3, b4, b5, b6, b7 = regression coefficients:
            ➢b1= -2,694
            ➢b2= 0,9809
            ➢b3= -7,868*10-3
            ➢b4= 0,05523
            ➢b5= 1,383
            ➢b6= 1,121*103
            ➢b7= 1,9
            The model is based on the following descriptors:
            [1] Molecular weight (MW). MW was calculated using KNIME platform.
            [2] Octanol water partition coefficient (log(Ko/w)). For the calculation of this descriptor, the AlogP VEGA model has been used.</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>The model has been developed by:
        Alberto Manganaro; Kode srl info@kode-solutions.net

        The original equation is described here:
        Wil ten Berge, A simple dermal absorption model: Derivation and application. 2009, 75, 1440–1445 https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S004565350900232X

        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>Skin permeability coefficient (Kp) represents the rate of chemicals penetrating across the skin. In this model the prediction is provided as logKp. The experimental protocol is based on the OECD 428 guideline.
        Species: human skin in vitro from aqueous solutions</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>271</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.58</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.72</RMSE_Train>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>