<xml>

    <Version>
        <Name>Fish Acute (LC50) Toxicity model (IRFMN-Combase)</Name>
        <Key>FISH_COMBASE</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for acute toxicity (LC50) in fish, specific for biocides</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>

    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_fish_combase.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>-log(mmol/l)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a quantitative prediction of acute toxicity in Fish (LC50), given in -log(mmol/L) and converted in mg/L. It has been developed inside the EU LIFE COMBASE project
            (LIFE15 ENV/ES/416). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vegahub.eu.</Description>
        <Model>88 biocides with experimental data on LC50 96h for Fish Acute Toxicity (expressed as –Log mmol/L in base 10). Toxicity data were searched on several public sources and literature databases:

            - the Office of Pesticide Programs (OPP) Pesticides Ecotoxicity Database (http://www.ipmcenters.org/ecotox/)),
            - the ECOTOX (https://cfpub.epa.gov/ecotox/) database.
            - the OECD QSAR toolbox (www.qsartoolbox.org),
            - the Pesticide Properties Database (PPDB) database (https://sitem.herts.ac.uk/aeru/ppdb/en),
            - AMBIT (http://cefic-lri.org/toolbox/ambit/) database.

            The data were selected considering all the criteria required by OECD 203 guideline.

            CORAL (http://www.insilico.eu/coral) was used to develop a regression QSAR model from SMILES-based optimal descriptors. A CORAL mathematical model describes the relationship between an endpoint (dependent variable) and relevant SMILES attributes (independent variable), as explained in:

            Toropov, A.A., Toropova, A.P., Roncaglioni, A., Benfenati, E. "Prediction of biochemical endpoints by the CORAL software: Prejudices, Paradoxes, and Results" (2018) Methods in Molecular Biology, 1800, pp. 573-583.

            The final model formula obtained with CORAL is:

            Endpoint =  -0.9887356 (± 0.1138834) + 0.0454373 (± 0.0013499) * DCW(1,15)

            where DCW is represented by the following formula, see section 1.4 for the list of CORAL fragments used in the model and their correlation weights:
        </Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Active_Train>22</n_Active_Train>
        <R2_Active_Train>0.7908</R2_Active_Train>
        <Q2_Active_Train>0.7422</Q2_Active_Train>
        <RMSE_Active_Train>0.890</RMSE_Active_Train>
        <F_Active_Train>76</F_Active_Train>
        <n_Passive_Train>22</n_Passive_Train>
        <R2_Passive_Train>0.8323</R2_Passive_Train>
        <Q2_Passive_Train>0.8051</Q2_Passive_Train>
        <RMSE_Passive_Train>1.40</RMSE_Passive_Train>
        <F_Passive_Train>99</F_Passive_Train>
        <n_Calibration>22</n_Calibration>
        <R2_Calibration>0.8351</R2_Calibration>
        <Q2_Calibration>0.8004</Q2_Calibration>
        <RMSE_Calibration>0.707</RMSE_Calibration>
        <F_Calibration>101</F_Calibration>
        <n_Validation>22</n_Validation>
        <R2_Validation>0.7931</R2_Validation>
        <RMSE_Validation>0.740</RMSE_Validation>
    </Stats>

</xml>