<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Daphnia Magna Chronic (NOEC) Toxicity model (IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>DAPHNIA_NOEC</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for chronic toxicity (NOEC) in daphnia magna</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.2</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_daphnia_noec.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>log(mmol/l)</Units>

    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The Daphnia Chronic (NOEC) toxicity model (IRFMN) –v.1.0.0 is based on 306 experimental data retrieved from the Japanese Ministry of Environment (http://www.env.go.jp/en/chemi/sesaku/aquatic_Mar_2016.pdf) and selected according to the OECD TG 211 requirements. The model is a Tree Ensemble Random Forest.</Description>
        <Dataset>The model is based on 306 experimental data.
            Pre-processing of data before modelling
            SMILES creation and neutralization:
            Firstly, we generated the SMILES structures from the chemical name and CAS RN for each substance using ChemCell (2019) and Marvin View (Marvin 17.28.0, 2012017, ChemAxon, 2019). We manually checked the correspondence and correctness among the obtained structures, chemical name and CAS RN among several websites and public database like ChemIDplus Advanced ( NIH, 2019), PubChem (NCBI, 2019), ChemSpider (Royal Society of Chemistry, 2019), DSSTox. Then, we added several structures, which have not automatically generated.
            We normalized the SMILES with istMolBase 1.0.3. (in-house software), then we neutralized them using KNIME 3.5. Since pH is acritical issue in the experimental assays on algae, we considered ionized normalized SMILES and we calculated the major microspecies at pH 7.5 and 8.1 using JChem for Excel. We removed the compounds for which the SMILES changed depending on pH (in range 7.5-8.1).
            Cleaning of the structure:
            We cleaned the datasets excluding the following compounds:
            metal complexes
            inorganics
            mixtures of structural isomers
            ambiguous structures
            non-ionic surfactant mixtures
            complex disconnected structures (e.g. polymers)
            chemicals whose correspondence name-CAS was not found.
            UVCB:
            salts; only the acid form was kept.
            Values cleaning:
            We selected continuous experimental values excluding those reported as a range, greater/less than a certain threshold, or approximate values. We converted each experimental value from mg/l to mmol/l, on the basis of the molecular weight calculated from the chemical structure. We also removed the compounds for which the experimental toxicity values were higher than the experimental water solubility values. For this purpose, we retrieved the experimental water solubility values mainly from a large database of more than 4,000 chemicals that we pruned in the LIFE project ANTARES and from GuideChem and Sigma-Aldrich websites in the case we did not find the water solubilities elsewhere.
            Dealing with multiple values:
            To deal with multiple continuous data we referred to the procedures described in ECHA guidance R.10 (2008) for ecotoxicological continuous endpoints. In case the experimental conditions and the reliability of the studies were the same, we considered the ratio between the maximum and the minimum values; if it was higher than one log unit we eliminated the data. Then, we calculated the median, the arithmetic and geometric mean in mmol/l to check if there were differences among them. We found a very good correlation between the values of each combination (arithmetic vs geometric mean, arithmetic mean vs median, geometric mean vs median) and finally the geometric mean was preferred (ECHA guidance R.10, 2008). To normalize the data we performed two types of transformation, the logarithm of the geometric mean and the Box-cox transformation. Since the box-cox transformation gave better results in terms of normalization of the data, it was finally used to normalize the data. We excluded data falling outside the range (mean of the box-cox transformed values) ± 3*(standard deviation).
            Availability of the training set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the training set: All
            Availability of the external validation set: No
            Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set: All
            Other information about the training set: To derive the models, we divided the data in training and test sets with the ratio of 80:20.</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>The model is a Tree Ensemble Random Forest.
            To derive the models, we divided the data in training and test sets with the ratio of 80:20. In order to obtain a uniform distribution of the endpoint values between the two subsets we applied an activity and descriptors sampling method. We performed a Principal Component Analysis (PCA) on all the descriptors and we selected the first two principal components. We selected five random compounds, and then we picked the most dissimilar compound from the sample pool according to the first two principal components and the response using several combinations of distance metrics and scoring functions. Then we added the compound to the pool repeating the operation until we reached the desired number for the training set.
            Among the several algorithms used, we obtained the best results in terms of performance with a Random Forest called Tree ensemble. Tree ensemble builds a series of regression trees with different rows and different variables (according to certain parameters) and then it aggregates the results as an ensemble of models. It chooses the parameters for the variables of each tree and the number of compounds evaluating the performance of several models (Hyperparameter tuning Research) using as metric R2 of a Bootstrap (100 iterations) cross-validation on training set.
            Dragon 7.0 extension for KNIME has been used to calculate the descriptors, resulting in 3839 2D descriptors. Then we applied a pruning process both to the compounds and to the descriptors pools. Firstly, we removed the compounds for which it was not feasible to calculate AlogP (octanol-water partition coefficient (Ghose and Crippen, 1986; Viswanadhan et al., 1993; Ghose et al., 1998)), as it is generally well acknowledged that this descriptor is the most correlated to the response. Then, to reduce the great number of variables, we removed all the descriptors with constant values (var(X) = 0), or which correlate over 0.95 (Pearson) with at least one another descriptor. In order to select the variables we used two methods implemented in R packages for each dataset: the genetic algorithm (gaselect package) and the Variable Selection Using Random Forest (VSURF) package. We imported both the pools of variables of each dataset into a KNIME workflow to derive the models.</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 => index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>The model has been developed by Cosimo Toma in 2019.
        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>The endpoint is the long-term toxicity to aquatic invertebrates according to ECOTOX 6.1.4. The species is named Daphnids (Daphnia magna).</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Tot>307.0</n_Tot>
        <R2_Toyt>0.61</R2_Toyt>
        <RMSE_Tot>0.71</RMSE_Tot>
        <mean_obs_Tot>-2.50</mean_obs_Tot>
        <n_Train>215.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.64</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.66</RMSE_Train>
        <mean_obs_Train>-2.52</mean_obs_Train>
        <n_Test>92.0</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.57</R2_Test>
        <RMSE_Test>0.81</RMSE_Test>
        <mean_obs_Test>-2.4</mean_obs_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>