<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>BCF model (KNN-Read-Across)</Name>
        <Key>BCF_KNN</Key>
        <Summary>KNN (Read-Across) model for fish BCF</Summary>
        <Version>1.1.0</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_bcf_knn.dat</TS>
        <Units>log(L/kg)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model performs a read-across and provides a quantitative prediction of bioconcentration factor (BCF) in fish, given in log(L/kg). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at: http://www.vega-qsar.eu/</Description>
        <Model>The model performs a read-across on a dataset of 860 chemicals. This dataset has been made by Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri, merging experimental data from several reliable sources, including the original dataset of the CAESAR BCF model (note that experimental values may differ from the ones in the CAESAR BCF dataset, as this new dataset has been built including more sources). The read-across model has been built with the istKNN application (developed by Kode srl, http://chm.kode-solutions.net) and it is based on the similarity index developed inside the VEGA platform; the index takes into account several structural aspects of the compounds, such as their fingerprint, the number of atoms, of cycles, of heteroatoms, of halogen atoms, and of particular fragments (such as nitro groups). The index value ranges from 1 (maximum similarity) to 0
            On the basis of this structural similarity index, the four compounds from the dataset resulting most similar to the chemical to be predicted are taken into account; compounds with a similarity value lower than 0.7 are discarded, and if only one compound remains available for prediction, it is kept only if it has a similarity value higher than 0.75. If no compounds fall under these conditions, no prediction is provided. Furthermore, if the range of experimental values observed in the chosen molecules is higher than 3.5 log units, no prediction is provided. The estimated BCF value is calculated as the weighted average value of the experimental values of the chosen compounds, using their similarity values as weight. Their similarity values are raised to the power of 3 in order to enhance the weight of the most similar compounds in the calculated prediction.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.75</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.75 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt;= 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that slightly disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index > 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that completely disagree with the target compound predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>836.0</n>
        <R2>0.665</R2>
        <RMSE>0.759</RMSE>
        <Not_Predicted>24.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>