<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Chromosomal aberration model (CORAL)</Name>
        <Key>CHROM_CORAL</Key>
        <Summary>Classification model for chromosomal aberration</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>

    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_chrom_coral.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>Not predicted</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Inactive</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Active</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model is based on experiments with Chromosomal aberration.
            Comment on endpoint: Structural aberrations may be of two types, chromosome or chromatid. Polyploidy (including endoreduplication) could arise in chromosome aberration assays in vitro. While aneugens can induce polyploidy, polyploidy alone does not indicate aneugenic potential and can simply indicate cell cycle perturbation or cytotoxicity. Chromosome aberrations, including breakage, rearrangement, and change in the number of chromosomes in the metaphase, have been associated with carcinogenicity and developmental effects.
            Type of model: One-variable model based on SMILES-derived descriptors.</Description>
        <Model>The model has been developed by:
            Andrey A. Toropov, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy (andrey.toropov@marionegri.it) https://www.marionegri.it/
            Alla P. Toropova, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy (alla.toropova@marionegri.it ) https://www.marionegri.it/
            Giuseppa Raitano, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156 Milano, Italy (giuseppa.raitano @marionegri.it) https://www.marionegri.it/</Model>
        <Dataset>The model is based on experiments with Chromosomal aberrations.
            Endpoint units: The model provides a quantitative prediction for chromosomal aberrations in a continuous number between +1 (active) and -1 (inactive). The threshold to discriminate between active and inactive is 0 (&lt; 0 is inactive; > 0 is active).
            Dependent variable: One-variable model based on optimal descriptor.
            Experimental protocol: According to OECD 473 guideline, the purpose of the in vitro chromosomal aberration test is to identify substances that cause structural chromosomal aberrations in cultured mammalian cells. This test is not designed to measure aneuploidy. The analysis of chromosomal aberration induction should be done using cells in metaphase. It is thus essential that cells should reach mitosis both in treated and in untreated cultures. Cell cultures of human or other mammalian origin are exposed to the test chemical both with and without an exogenous source of metabolic activation unless cells with an adequate metabolizing capability are used. At an appropriate predetermined interval after the start of exposure of cell cultures to the test chemical, they are treated with a metaphase-arresting substance (e.g. Colcemid® or colchicine), harvested, stained and metaphase cells are analyzed microscopically for the presence of chromatid-type and chromosome-type aberrations.
            Endpoint data quality and variability: Experimental data for this work were taken from the Genotoxicity OASIS Database (http://oasis-lmc.org/products/databases/rat-liver-metabolism-extended.aspx) and the Toxicity Japan MHLW (http://dra4.nihs.go.jp/mhlw_data/jsp/SearchPageENG.jsp) that include data for chromosomal aberrations determined by in vitro test using Chinese hamster lung (CHL) and ovary (CHO) cells, with and without metabolic activation (metabolic system S9). Data were selected on the basis of their compliance with OECD 473 guideline.
            Pre-processing of data before modelling: The SMILES have been normalized by the VEGA platform (www.vegahub.eu/).
            Availability of the training set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the training set: Yes
            Availability of the external validation set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set: Yes
            Other information about the training set: The initial dataset was divided five times into sets (training, calibration, and validation) using a random distribution.
            Other information about the external validation set: Non-available</Dataset>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>Type of model: One-variable model based on SMILES-derived descriptors.
            Explicit algorithm: CORAL (http://www.insilico.eu/coral/), which is based on the Monte Carlo method.

            Chromosomal aberrations = -0.604 (± 0.002) +    0.0614 (± 0.0001) * DCW(1,13)

            Category={active  if, y≥0.5 inactive if,y&lt;0.5

            Algorithm and descriptor generation: The Monte Carlo Method
            Software name and version for descriptor generation:
            CORAL 2017, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCCS, 20156 Milano, Italy
            http://www.insilico.eu/coral/
            The model uses optimal 2D descriptors.
            insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors in the model: SMILES-derived optimal descriptor DCW(T*,N*)
            Descriptor selection: SMILES-derived optimal descriptor, according to the equation:


            The “descriptors”, SMILES attributes, are based on SMILES, and refer to short sequences of characters (up to three). The model identifies these SMILES attributes which are statistically significant. The other are excluded. In this way these SMILES attributes are selected, through the Monte Carlo method.

            Algorithm and descriptor generation: The Monte Carlo Method
            Software name and version for descriptor generation:
            CORAL 2017, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCCS, 20156 Milano, Italy
            http://www.insilico.eu/coral/</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 0.8 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 0.8</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>Date of model development and/or publication: May 9, 2018

        It has been described here: A.A. Toropov, A.P. Toropova, G. Raitano, E. Benfenati, CORAL: building up QSAR models for the chromosome aberration test. Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences, 26 (2019), 1101–1106. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sjbs.2018.05.013

        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G. VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>Species: Data for chromosomal aberrations determined by in vitro test using Chinese hamster lung (CHL) and ovary (CHO) cells, with and without metabolic activation (metabolic system S9).
        Endpoint: Chromosomal aberrations
        Comment on endpoint: Structural aberrations may be of two types, chromosome or chromatid. Polyploidy (including endoreduplication) could arise in chromosome aberration assays in vitro. While aneugens can induce polyploidy, polyploidy alone does not indicate aneugenic potential and can simply indicate cell cycle perturbation or cytotoxicity. Chromosome aberrations, including breakage, rearrangement, and change in the number of chromosomes in the metaphase, have been associated with carcinogenicity and developmental effects.
        Endpoint units: The model provides a quantitative prediction for chromosomal aberrations in a continuous number between +1 (active) and -1 (inactive). The threshold to discriminate between active and inactive is 0 (&lt; 0 is inactive; > 0 is active).</Endpoint>

    <Stats></Stats>
    
</xml>