<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Water solubility model (IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>WS_IRFMN</Key>
        <Summary>Quantitative model for water solubility.</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_watersolubility_irfmn.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <Units>-log(mol/L)</Units>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The Water solubility model is based on Artificial Neural Network (ANN) in which the modelled endpoint is a physical chemical property is based on the dataset retrieved from TEST software that consist of 5020 chemicals from the EPISuiteTM database (US EPA. EPI Suite, Version 4.0. US EPA, 2019 (accessed 5/21/09))</Description>
        <Model>The model has been developed by Alberto Manganaro, Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri IRCSS Via Mario Negri 2, 20156. Milano, Italy alberto.manganaro@marionegri.it https://www.marionegri.it/
            It has been described here:
            “Benfenati E, Roncaglioni A, Lombardo A, Manganaro A. Integrating QSAR, Read Across, and Screening Tools: The VEGAHUB Platform as an Example. Advances in Computational Toxicology; Springer; 20 19. p. 365 81.”
            For a general description of the VEGA software see:
            Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
            VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
            Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
            Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Model>
        <Dataset>The model is based on the dataset retrieved from TEST software that consist of 5020 chemicals from the EPISuiteTM database (US EPA. EPI Suite, Version 4.0. US EPA.a, 2019 (accessed 5/21/09)) 09)). Chemicals with water solubilities exceeding 1,000,000 mg/L were omitted from the overall dataset. In addition, data were limited to data points that are within 10°C of 25°C.
            The protocol for the test varied through the decades, including limit test and up down procedure. No details about the protocol are associated to each experimental data point used for the modelling.
            Availability of the training set: Yes
            Data for the dependent variable for the training set: All
            Availability of external validation set: Yes
            Data for each dependent variable for the external validation set: All</Dataset>
        <Descriptors>The Artificial Neural Network (ANN) has been trained with the 'nnet' package in the software platform R and exported as a PMML, using DRAGON descriptors.
            Software name and version for the descriptor generation:
            DRAGON (v. 7.0).
            Calculation of several sets of molecular descriptors from molecular geometries (topological, geometrical, WHIM, 3D MoRSE, molecular profiles, etc.)
            Prof. R.Todeschini - distributed by Talete srl, via Pisani 13, 20124 Milano, Italy
            http://www.disat.unimib.it/chm
            The selected descriptors have been implemented in VEGA.
            VEGA (https://www.vegahub.eu/)
            The VEGA software provides QSAR models to predict tox, ecotox, environ, phys-chem and toxicokinetic properties of chemical substances.
            emilio.benfenati@marionegri.it
            The model uses 15 molecular descriptors calculated within the VEGA descriptors and based on the Dragon software calculation and definition:
            ALogP
            piPC8
            SEigm
            MATS1v
            PW6
            P_VSA_i_4
            LogP
            nR10
            CATS2D_4_DL
            BEH2p
            BIC3
            GATS2m
            H-050
            D/Dr3
            CATS2D_7_DL
            An in-house tool developed in the R statistical platform has been used to select the best descriptors set and size to be employed for the final model. The approach was based on a forward selection technique: starting from the descriptor most correlated with the experimental data, at each iteration the descriptor leading to the best model (among all the available descriptors) was added, until the size of 25 descriptors. Models have been built, with a linear regression modelling, applied with a bootstrap cross-validation approach (n =
            100). For each model, the fitness function has been calculated as the R squared coefficient obtained from the models built in each bootstrap iteration.
            This fitness function has been used to select the best descriptor to be added to proceed to the next iteration. From this procedure, the set of descriptors with the best cross-validation values has been chosen as the set to be used for the final model. The "best" values have been considered taking into account their trend: by progressively adding descriptors to the model, the cross-validation performances increase until a plateau (and, following, a decrease), which means that the optimal number of descriptors have been reached, and adding further descriptors would lead to over-fitting.</Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 > index > 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index => 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Maximum_Error</Name>
                <RangeTop>index &lt; 0.6</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a low value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.6 &lt;= index &lt; 1.2</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a moderate value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index >= 1.2</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>the maximum error in prediction of similar molecules found in the training set has a high value, considering the experimental variability</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.85</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.85 >= index > 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint>The endpoint of the model is a physical- chemical property, the water solubility (P-CHEM, 4.8) (-Log(mol/L)).</Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>4014.0</n_Train>
        <R2_Train>0.857</R2_Train>
        <RMSE_Train>0.833</RMSE_Train>
        <n_Test>1004.0</n_Test>
        <R2_Test>0.824</R2_Test>
        <RMSE_Test>0.935</RMSE_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>