<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Bee acute toxicity model (KNN-IRFMN)</Name>
        <Key>BEE_KNN</Key>
        <Summary>KNN model for bee contact and oral acute toxicity</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.0</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_bee_knn.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>Strong toxicity (lower than 1 µg/bee)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Moderate toxicity (between 1 and 100 µg/bee)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>2</Value>
                <Label>Low toxicity (over 100 µg/bee)</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-999</Value>
                <Label>Non Predicted</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative evaluation (3 toxicity classes) for acute contact toxicity in honeybees (Apis Mellifera). It has been developed using a k-NN modelling approach, by Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri. </Description>
        <Model>The model has been built as a k-NN model developed on a set of 256 with known experimental toxicity data, following the original work available soon (in a paper under submission stage):
            Como F, Carnesecchi E, Volani S, Dorne J L, Richardson J C, Bassan A, Pavan M, Benfenati E “Predicting acute contact toxicity of pesticides in honeybees (Apis Mellifera) through a k-Nearest Neighbor model”, Chemosphere
            The dataset contains experimental data binned in 3 toxicity classes: lower than 1 µg/bee (strong toxicity), between 1 and 100 µg/bee (moderate toxicity), over 100 µg/bee (low toxicity).
            This model has been built with the istKNN application (developed by Kode srl, http://chm.kode-solutions.net) and it is based on the similarity index developed inside the VEGA platform; the index takes into account several structural aspects of the compounds, such as their fingerprint, the number of atoms, of cycles, of heteroatoms, of halogen atoms, and of particular fragments (such as nitro groups). The index value ranges from 1 (maximum similarity) to 0. On the basis of this structural similarity index, the four compounds from the dataset resulting most similar to the chemical to be predicted are taken into account; compounds with a similarity value lower than 0.7 are discarded, and if only one compound remains available for prediction, it is kept only if it has a similarity value higher than 0.75. If no compounds fall under these conditions, no prediction is provided. The prediction is calculated as the most representative class in the compound selected with the above mentioned procedure, considering their similarity index values as a weight so that the most similar compounds have an higher influence in the prediction.
            While the original model has been built splitting the dataset in a training and test set, the current implementation uses all 256 compounds as training set to enhance the k-NN performances.</Model>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index >= 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n>256.0</n>
        <Specificity>0.853</Specificity>
        <Sensitivity>0.681</Sensitivity>
        <Accuracy>0.777</Accuracy>
        <Not_Predicted>0.0</Not_Predicted>
    </Stats>
    
</xml>