<xml>
   
    <Version>
        <Name>Cramer classification (TOXTREE)</Name>
        <Key>CRAMER_TOXTREE</Key>
        <Summary>Cramer classification from ToxTree 3.1.</Summary>
        <Version>1.0.1</Version>
    </Version>
    
    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_cramer_toxtree.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>false</HasAlerts>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>
            The Cramer rules Model is based on the Cramer classification scheme as implemented in the module Cramer rules of Toxtree. This model does not refer to a collection of experimental data on a certain endpoint. It is structural based model which aims to identify rules of concern, and thus it is not a statistical model, but it is closer to an expert system.</Description>
        <Model>
            The original model implements the conceptual scheme developed by Cramer. For the implementation in ToxTree: Nina jeliazkova; IDEA Consult, Joseph II straat 40 B1, 1000 Brussels, Belgium; jeliazkova.nina@gmail.com</Model>
        <Dataset>
            Endpoint units: Adimensional
            Dependent variable: The dependent variable is the severity of the effect, as three classes: 1 (lower concern), 2 (intermediate concern), 3 (higher concern).
            Experimental protocol: NA
            Endpoint data quality and variability: NA
            Pre-processing of data before modelling: NA
            Availability of the training set: The decision tree is not a statistical model, with a training set. The software identifies the presence of certain fragments and features associated to the Cramer classes.
            Data for the dependent variable for the training set: NA
            Availability of the external validation set: NA
            Data for the dependent variable for the external validation set: All
            Other information about the training set: NA
            Other information about the external validation set: NA</Dataset>
        <Descriptors>
            The VEGA implementation of Cramer classification is a structure-based model based on the Cramer classification scheme. Ad hoc decision tree has been implemented within Toxtree, and the same tree is implemented in VEGA.
            The model is a structure-based model and does not make use of descriptors</Descriptors>
    </Guide>

    <Reference>
        The Toxtree model has been implemented in VEGA by Alberto Manganaro; IRCCS-Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche Mario Negri, Via La Masa 19, 20156 Milano, Italy; alberto.manganaro@marionegri.it in 2020.
        It has been described here:
        1. Cramer G. M., R. A. Ford, R. L. Hall, Estimation of Toxic Hazard - A Decision Tree Approach, J. Cosmet. Toxicol., Vol.16, pp. 255-276, Pergamon Press, 1978.
        2. I.C. Munro, R.A. Ford, E. Kennepohl, and J.G. Sprenger, Correlation of structural class with No    Observed-Effect Levels: A proposal for establishing a threshold of concern, Food Chem. Toxicol. 34 (1996), pp. 829-867.
        3. Patlewicz G, Jeliazkova N, Safford RJ, Worth AP, Aleksiev B. (2008) An evaluation of the implementation of the Cramer classification scheme in the Toxtree software. SAR QSAR Environ Res. ;19(5-6):495-524.
        For a general description of the VEGA software see:
        Benfenati E, Manganaro A, Gini G
        VEGA-QSAR: AI inside a platform for predictive toxicology
        Proceedings of the workshop "Popularize Artificial Intelligence 2013", December 5th 2013, Turin, Italy
        Published on CEUR Workshop Proceedings Vol-1107</Reference>

    <Endpoint>
        This model does not refer to a collection of experimental data on a certain endpoint. It aims to identify rules of concern, and thus it is not a statistical model, but it is closer to an expert system. The species is not applicable. Ideally it refers to human toxicity.</Endpoint>

    <Stats></Stats>
    
</xml>