<xml>

    <Version>
        <Name>Skin Sensitization model (CAESAR)</Name>
        <Key>SKIN_CAESAR</Key>
        <Summary>QSAR classification model for Skin sensitization (from CAESAR project)</Summary>
        <Version>2.1.7</Version>
    </Version>

    <Vega>
        <TS>/data/ts_skin_caesar.dat</TS>
        <HasAlerts>False</HasAlerts>
        <ClassValues>
            <Class>
                <Value>0</Value>
                <Label>NON-Sensitizer</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>1</Value>
                <Label>Sensitizer</Label>
            </Class>
            <Class>
                <Value>-1</Value>
                <Label>Not Classifiable</Label>
            </Class>
        </ClassValues>
    </Vega>

    <Guide>
        <Description>The model provides a qualitative prediction of skin sensitisation on mouse (local lymph node assay model). It is implemented inside the VEGA online platform, accessible at:http://www.vega-qsar.eu/
            The model extends the original CAESAR model, freely available at: http://www.caesar-project.eu/software/</Description>
        <Model>The model consists in an Adaptive Fuzzy Partition (AFP) based on 8 descriptors. The AFP produces as output two values O(positive) and O(negative) that represent the belonging degree respectively to the sensitizer and non-sensitizer classes. The input compound is assigned to the class having this degree value higher than 0.5, unless the difference between the values of the two degrees is lower than the threshold 0.001; in this case, the belonging to one class or the other is not sure, thus no prediction is made. Full reference and details of the used formulas can be found in:
            Chaudhry, Q., Piclin, N., Cotterill, J., Pintore, M., Price, N. R., Chrétien, J. R. and Roncaglioni, A. (2010). Global QSAR models of skin sensitisers for regulatory purposes., Chem Cent J 4 Suppl 1, S5.</Model>
        <insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>The descriptors used by the AFP model are the following:
            - nN: Number of nitrogen atoms
            - GNar: Narumi geometrc topological index
            - MDDD: Mean Distance Degree Deviation
            - X2v: Valence connectivity index chi-2
            - EEig10r: Eigenvalue 10 from the edge adjacency matrix weighted by resonance integrals
            - GGI8: Topological charge index of order 8
            - nCconj: Number of non aromatic conjugated C(sp2)
            - O-058: Atom-centred fragment =O
            The descriptors were calculated, in the original model, by means of MDL and dragonX software and are now entirely calculated by an in-house software module in which they are implemented as described in: R. Todeschini and V. Consonni, Molecular insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors for Chemoinformatics, Wiley-VCH, 2009.</insilico.dilibayer.Descriptors>
        <Applicability_Domain>
            <AD>
                <Name>Similar_Molecules</Name>
                <SimilarMols>3</SimilarMols>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>strongly similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>only moderately similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>no similar compounds with known experimental value in the training set have been found</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Accuracy</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is good</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not optimal</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>accuracy of prediction for similar molecules found in the training set is not adequate</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Concordance</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index > 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that agree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 >= index > 0.6 </RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt;= 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>similar molecules found in the training set have experimental values that disagree with the predicted value</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>ACF_SimCheck</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = 1</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>all atom centered fragment of the compound have been found in the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>1 > index >= 0.7</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>some atom centered fragment of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.7</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>a prominent number of atom centered fragments of the compound have not been found in the compounds of the training set or are rare fragments</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>Model_Descriptors_Range_Check</Name>
                <RangeTop>index = True</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>descriptors for this compound have values inside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeBottom>index = False</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>descriptors for this compound have values outside the descriptor range of the compounds of the training set</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
            <AD>
                <Name>AD_Index</Name>
                <RangeTop>1 >= index >= 0.8</RangeTop>
                <DescriptionRangeTop>predicted substance is into the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeTop>
                <RangeMid>0.8 > index >= 0.6</RangeMid>
                <DescriptionRangeMid>predicted substance could be out of the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeMid>
                <RangeBottom>index &lt; 0.6</RangeBottom>
                <DescriptionRangeBottom>predicted substance is out of the the Applicability Domain of the model</DescriptionRangeBottom>
            </AD>
        </Applicability_Domain>
    </Guide>

    <Reference></Reference>

    <Endpoint></Endpoint>

    <Stats>
        <n_Train>167.0</n_Train>
        <Specificity_Train>0.794</Specificity_Train>
        <Sensitivity_Train>0.955</Sensitivity_Train>
        <Accuracy_Train>0.922</Accuracy_Train>
        <n_Test>42.0</n_Test>
        <Specificity_Test>0.75</Specificity_Test>
        <Sensitivity_Test>0.971</Sensitivity_Test>
        <Accuracy_Test>0.929</Accuracy_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Test>0.0</Not_Predicted_Test>
        <Not_Predicted_Train>0.0</Not_Predicted_Train>
    </Stats>

</xml>